[Automated Newsletter Service
for your valuable community]
Hello everybody, welcome to my session.
My name is Chansung Park, and
I am one of the administrators
at TensorFlow Korea community.
Today I'm here to share my own experience
on how I have improved the
quality of the community
by creating something as shown in title,
Automated Newsletter Service.
This newsletter service
is an open source project,
and was built specifically for
TensorFlow Korea community.
But you'll see some general concepts
and the way how to apply
it for your own community.
So here are some of the topics
that I wanna cover today.
First, I wanna give a
little bit of background
about what TensorFlow Korea community is
in order to give you sense of what it is,
and why the newsletter
service might be a good thing.
Second, I'll share some of my experiences,
mostly bad experiences while interacting
with the community over the past one year.
By doing so, you'll understand what exactly
motivated me to create such service.
Third, I'm going through some
of the implementation details,
this is not about giving you
how to write the actual code,
but to give you a sense, what are
the components needed to form such service,
and what are the pipelines
looks like to run the service.
The fourth one is a
part of the third topic,
the newsletter service could be run
as a standalone application locally,
but it would be nice to send
out newsletters automatically.
You'll see how we can
leverage GitHub Action
for automated weekly newsletter service.
And last but not least,
I'll give you a brief talk
about the current status of the service,
and the future plan that
I'm working on these days
to improve the service any further.
So let's begin.
TensorFlow Korea is a community originated
for sharing information and experiences
about TensoerFlow framework.
TensorFlow code is an open source project
and is for machine learning
and deep learning project.
And it was created by Google, by the way,
it's based on Facebook group,
and it started out its
own journey in 2016,
I mean, TensorFlow Korea community
not the TensorFlow
framework, that was just
an year after the born
of TensorFlow framework.
And we have reached about
50,000 members about a month ago.
It was a very important
milestone for our community,
so the newsletter service
that I will explain
was designed for celebrating and returning
back event for our community members.
Despite of its original purpose,
there is a variety of topics that
we discuss these days in our community.
As you know, AI itself is not a big deal,
but when it's combined with
different technologies,
it becomes a huge deal.
Because of that, we have
a very large user base
from lots of different backgrounds.
Interesting part is,
our members are posting
not only simple Q&As but also
complex topics and some useful information.
They're labeled by very
rich text and images.
There's quite different aspect
from other communities, I think.
Also we are holding lots of
great events online and offline.
During the COVID-19 pandemic,
we have held awesome
on-tech online seminars
with a Leader of Google AI advocate,
Professor Cho Kyunghyun
from New York University,
and NVIDIA engineer from Silicon Valley.
Let me show you some of the showcases
that we frequently share
through this community.
Most of all, as you can see,
many posts are very
rich and well organized.
On the right hand side,
ah, on the left hand side,
the screenshot shows that we share
some news that's happening globally,
and encourage members
to join the discussion via comments.
Also, since members use
lots of different tools
to realize AI for their own purpose,
we wanna share tips and useful
information about the tools.
This is not just for TensorFlow framework,
but it's for everything.
You can frequently find out information
related to PyTorch, Jags
and other frameworks,
and whatever you're looking for.
And this kind of post sometimes includes
the actual code snippets,
I think it is super useful.
The third example is a bit crazy, but yes,
some of our members are researchers,
and they're happy to share paper reviews,
and their own thoughts about it.
We actually have a group
of people recording
and sharing their paper
reviews every week.
Also, ethical issue is
an important part in AI.
As shown for the example,
our members want to share
ethical topics and eager
to listen to what other
people think about the topics.
AI is rapidly evolving area,
so it's also good thing
to have some people who share
recent trends and their limitations.
Now, these are just a tiny bit of what's
happening in TensorFlow Korea community,
but by looking at these examples,
you could get some sense
that we have very rich
information floating around.
So this was the first thing
that developed my intuition
to create the newsletter service,
because I didn't wanna lose
all the information after all.
As you know, it's not easy to hold
past information in Facebook though.
Here, let's look at
some numbers this time.
By inspecting some numbers,
this idea could be developed
much more concrete and strong.
On the top left corner,
the graph shows constantly
increasing number of members,
meaning we are possibly having more
and more people to share rich information.
Also we have a constant number
of active members over the last year,
this clearly shows many of our members are
happy about the community.
On the right hand side, you
can see there are two graphs
showing the number of
posts for the past 60 days
and seven days respectively.
As you can see, we have a
list of 150 posts every week,
you might think it is small
number, when you think about
the number of members 50,000.
However, this is a huge number,
when you think about how well
the information is refined
as seen from the showcase.
As you can see, TensorFlow
Korea is a pretty good place
by looking at some of the statistical
numbers and actual showcase.
However, it turns out Facebook
group is not a great place
to archive and search
past information.
I wouldn't even have come up with the idea
to create a newsletter service if not so.
Who wants to share nicely
formatted information,
if it'll be dead the information
like after a month or so?
Here are some of the drawbacks
that I wanna point out,
which inspired me a lot.
These are drawbacks specifically
curated for Facebook Group,
but this might not be
true for your community.
But if you think your community
coincidentally has similar issues,
you could consider creating
a similar service for your own community.
At the end, I'll let you know how to bring
this open source project
into your own community.
So Facebook recommends what to
read for each Facebook user.
And Facebook keeps recommending
what you should read
based on your interest.
It's hard to keep following topics
that you have a little interest.
This could be a useful feature
if you wanna read what you're up to only.
However, in the case
that you want to expand
your interest to other areas,
that might be a bad feature.
According to the nature of our community,
this feature seems very inappropriate.
Like I said before, our members
have many different backgrounds,
so they are kind of new to AI field.
Also, consider the numbers that we
have just discussed in the previous slide,
it's almost impossible to consume
more than 150 posts every week,
even with top few posts like 20,
just ask yourself that
you could really digest
those information in a week, probably not,
especially when information
is not simple, but very rich.
Fixing these drawbacks could
led TensorFlow Korea community
to become much better place.
Also all the administrators
at TensorFlow Korea
always keep paying attention
to what we could give back
to our community members.
So with this background
in mind, I have created
a newsletter service to
solve some of those problems.
Here is a quick overview of it,
it is not a complicated service
nor it requires a lot
of Python coding skills
like it only took about
three weeks to launch.
Rather, it was just designed
to deliver rich information
to as many people as possible.
After receiving newsletters,
it is up to receivers
to archive if they want by
using a simple functions
in their mailbox like tagging function.
Out of 150 weekly posts,
up to 20 posts gets ranked
by a simple summation formula,
the number of reactions,
the number of shares,
and the number of comments.
It's possible to give
weights for each parameter,
so there's a customizable point.
For TensorFlow Korea, they're all set
to one for now, as an experimental purpose.
Also one of the great
features about this service
is the ability to issue
a weekly newsletter
without a human being involved.
That means it's fully automated,
and it's done through GitHub action.
I'll give a talk about
this topic just in shortly.
I have included all the
details about this project
in README, I think the
documentation has done nicely.
In the document, you can read the CLI spec
for this program, and I
believe CLI is the best way
to understand any project
features in a high level view.
So here's a sneak peek at it.
As you can see, there are some options
to make application
behave in different ways.
As we can set the range of dates when the,
to be scrapped post or posted by
using since then until flags.
Also, we could limit the
number of post to scrap.
Again, the weights for
each, different parameters
for the number of
reactions, number of shares,
number of comments are
all configurable as well.
On the right hand side,
the screenshot shows
a sample example uses,
so please check it out
if you're interested.
That was a pretty high level features
of what the application does.
Let's dive into bit more
details about the pipeline,
how the whole system
actually works in a nutshell.
The first thing it tries to do is
to read configurations from external files.
Configurations are split
into two categories,
sensitive and nonsensitive.
There are a number of
sensitive information,
including Facebook access token,
SMTP related information and et cetera.
Nonsensitive information is all about
what you can customize like
the number of top posts to be included,
how many words to include
for each post, and more.
Based on the configuration,
it tries to scrap Facebook
post in the group.
The returning values from Facebook server
are expressed in JSON format.
So we need to parse them
into Python objects.
The next step is to inject
parsed data into email template
which consists of HTML and CSS,
and injection is done
through Jinja2 library.
The next step is to send out
the formed email template
to the subscribers.
At this point, the main goal
will be achieved nicely.
But as you can see, there
are two additional steps,
refreshing Facebook token
and write configurations.
Refreshing Facebook tokens
are something inconvenient,
but necessary for some reasons.
I'll talk a bit more about that shortly.
"Write configuration" is to
update the Facebook token
with the refreshed one
into an external file
to make sure the token wouldn't
be expired in the next time,
because the token persist
for a certain range of time
so in order to keep everything works fine
after a week later,
a new token that will be still alive
should be written down
to the configuration file.
So this slide shows the
structure of the project.
Let me go through one by one real quick.
There are two directories, lib and static.
I put every internal logics
into a lib directory.
This includes data object
model, parsing logics,
creating email templates,
sending emails and so on.
On the other hand, I put something
without a logic into static folder.
It's more like constant
value stores in one place,
HTML templates are stored in here too.
Other than that, there are just
two more interesting files,
that env.gpg and config.cfg,
which are responsible
for sensitive and non sensitive
information respectively.
Just for experimental purpose
and self-learning purpose,
I have chosen that and that m-Python
and standard config parser package
for each file to insert and
extract information from them.
The remaining files are
pretty much self-explanatory,
so I don't think I need to give
any further explanations about them.
So let's talk about configuration now.
Like I said, there are two
separate configuration files.
In a development phase,
configurations are something
that should be changed very often time.
And it is the central place
where other users can touch
to port the project into
their own situations.
So I have found that keeping
the two very different information
separately is a good practice.
I don't wanna make any
difference whenever possible
for like application ID,
application secrete,
Facebook access token,
which should remain as
the same all the time.
Let's think about that,
I don't separate those.
Even though I'm not going
to change the information
that should remain as the same,
I should save it
and sync with the remote repository
whenever I modify
the configurable information.
Further more, sensitive information is
designed to be encrypted via GPG,
which stands for GNU Privacy Guard,
a server encryption algorithm.
After encryption is done,
all the information stays
as the same except for
the Facebook access token,
and passphrases managed to
GitHub secret by the way,
where you can put secret values
and reference back and GitHub Action,
so that you can decrypt that GPG file
with the passphrase without
letting anyone know about it.
On the other hand, config.cfg file
contains all the customizable information.
Just for your information,
Top K means the number of posts
to appear in a newsletter,
which is set to 24-hour.
And most importantly, Facebook
group ID is the ID of a group
where you wanna scrap post from.
The name of keys are pretty
much self-explanatory,
so please read it, if
you're interested in.
But let me move on to
the next topic for now,
which is Facebook access token.
Facebook access token is
something that you must acquire
if you wanna use Facebook Graph API.
In a normal process, you can
get the Facebook access token
for three major steps like,
you should create an Facebook app,
you should request on certain features
like group API for your app,
and your app must be
reviewed by Facebook team.
It doesn't look very
complicated process at all.
But the problem is, during
the COVID-19 pandemic,
Facebook has made a decision
to temporarily pause individual
verification process,
meaning you can't get the
access token in a normal way.
I was kind of shocked by
the fact because I was like,
how I get a post back from Facebook now,
is that even possible?
But luckily, after playing
around with the Facebook API
and reading Facebook official documents,
I found there's a workaround for this.
It goes like this.
First, you grab a temporary access token
via Graph API Explorer, which
is a playground for Graph API.
Exchange the temporary access
token with a long lived one,
Facebook provides an API for this.
Temporary access token only leaves
up to less than a day or so,
but the long lived one lives
up to more than a week.
So whenever graphing and parsing
Facebook post with the current token,
the current token will get refreshed
for the next run for the one more week,
because this is a weekly
newsletter service.
The refreshed token will be exported
into the dotenv and encrypted via gpg.
This was why we needed
two additional steps
at the end of the whole pipeline.
And this slide is for a snippet of
knowledge about Facebook's Graph API.
Graph API is nothing but a graph structure
that you probably studied
from algorithm class.
Everything can be expressed
with three concepts, node, edge and field.
Node is an entity and
the edge is a connection,
between nodes and fields
is a piece of information
dangling within a node.
For instance, group is a
node and posts are nodes,
and there are edges
between a group and posts.
And each post contains a number of fields
like date, contents, and so on.
It is somewhat a hard concept
when you have never heard about before.
Also, the version has been
dramatically changed over time.
And it already has reached version 8.0.
You might have read various
news about digital privacy,
so Facebook continuously
addressed new policies,
but the problem is that
they don't really make
any big announcement about
it for their developers.
But luckily, the only lucky
part and hope is that,
there is a graph API
Explorer as a place that
you can play with APIs, so
please use it whenever possible.
There's a tip for developers
who wanna deal with Facebook API.
So after parsing configuration,
what's gonna happen?
It's kind of boring steps.
But almost always, you
need a similar procedure,
when you try to scrap
information through API,
or crawling, is not
just only for Facebook.
Make HTTP requests to Facebook
server, is a good practice
to make this function
asynchronously working
because you don't want other
functions to be blocked.
And Facebook server
will give you back data
in the response which is in JSON format.
Because a raw JSON data
is not really accessible in Python, right?
So it should be properly
parsed into Python objects.
There are multiple ways
to achieve this goal,
but I have found it is easier
and much more readable
if you make a class method for this.
So class method is a central place,
which takes the incoming
raw JSON data format file.
And it extracts all the
information from the JSON,
and it creates an instance
of the Python object
if the JSON data is valid.
Based on parsed data, it'll
create a data model instance, like I said,
so that all the information
is much more accessible
for the rest of the program logics.
Based on parsed data within data model,
we can now inject them into HTML template.
HTML/CSS is easy, right?
But when it gets too long,
is not easily manageable,
even it gets worse when you
download a template from online,
because they contain some weird characters
that only their system understands.
Like Jinja2, we can split HTML
into several pieces of HTMLs
is like managing and importing
multiple sources of files in one project.
Also Jinja2 is probably
the most popular way
to inject Python information into HTML,
very flexible, and there
are nothing much to learn.
So which means syntax is straightforward,
so you could learn it just in a day.
I have additionally used Markdown2 package
before information injection.
Markdown2 is a tool to convert
an article written in
markdown format in HTML form.
Because basically, Facebook's posts
are written in Markdown format.
It won't be rendered appropriately,
if we don't make Markdown
syntax to be HTML compatible.
For instance, one hash character
often means a heading in Markdown.
But h1 tag is the counterpart in HTML.
So the so hash characters
should be converted into h1 tag.
Premailer packages also necessary package
if you consider email service,
since every CSS style should be in line
as attributes of every HTML tags,
that's a kind of normal thing in an email.
Otherwise almost every email clients
will not render things nicely,
and something will probably be broken.
I have not mentioned about the first step
in the email templating pipeline much,
it's all about your searching ability
to find out the best template.
But it's a real time consuming job,
if you don't have enough
skills in HTML and CSS,
looking for template line,
consider how much time
is going to be wasted.
For me, a week out of the whole
three weeks for this project
were wasted for only this process.
It's very fortunate to have free
service like Google Groups,
Google Groups is a central place
to dispatch an email to all subscribers.
So I just need to email the HTML template
to our Google Groups
and everyone in the group
will get the same email.
If you are planning to dispatch one email
template to a lot of people out there,
and wanna make sure they're
getting the same email all the time,
please use Google Groups.
I think that's the best solution for this.
So that is pretty much
everything you should know
about how to build a newsletter service.
This slide is kind of side note
to let you know what GitHub Action is,
and how we can make the job automatic.
First of all, you can choose
free or paid version for GitHub Action,
but you are almost always be satisfied
with the free version,
I guarantee you.
As you can see from the table,
there are only differences
about the size of storage
and running minutes of GitHub Action.
2000 minutes per month should
be enough for most of you.
You can also choose an operating
system for your needs too.
But just remember other
specs like CPU, RAM size,
other hardware specs
are, they're all the same
between the paid version and free version.
One particular reason that I
like about GitHub Action is,
I can easily overview how the
process goes in a project,
meaning GitHub Action illustrates
the high level workflow.
And it's very important
when you analyze an open source project.
I will probably say
this is the first place
that I'll visit for
any open source project
if they use GitHub Action.
However, one of the
drawbacks is the difficulties
during the GitHub Action testament,
you get to find out a way
to test Github Action locally.
Otherwise, you'll probably
end up with something
like 150 commits from this
slide, as you can see.
100 out of 150 reflects
the number of changes
that are needed to experiment
with a GitHub Action.
Luckily, recently I have found
there are a couple of ways
that you can test in a local environment.
One way is to pull GitHub Action event
from their local machine, and do something
within your local machine
based on the event.
That is the recommended way to do
and you can find the
information how to do it
from the GitHub Action official document.
The other way is to
leverage "nektos/act" project
which should lest you test
the whole GitHub Action
environment locally.
So please, for further information,
check out the official document
on "nektos/act" project homepage.
This slide shows the definition of
the GitHub Action workflow for this project.
Like I said, just by reading each line,
you'll understand the high level overview
about how this project works.
For instance, let's look
at the left hand side.
GitHub Action is scheduled
to be run every Friday at 3:00 AM,
which is 12:00 pm in South Korea.
Is just a simple cron job.
If you're familiar with cron job
from the Linux operating
system, is super easy.
Let me go through one red line
by one on the right hand side.
In order to pull encrypted information
from .M.GPG, it should
be decrypted first, right?
And some environment variables
are set to be used as
arguments of the main program.
That's the second red line.
And program gets run and the email
should be successfully sent
by the end of this process.
And the access token
should be refreshed by now,
with a new one for the next one more week.
The refreshed token gets
written down to the .env
and .env will be encrypted again via GPG.
Since .env gpg is updated,
it should be pushed to the master branch.
So the update information will persist
for the next one more week.
It is very straightforward
and you'll get the sense how
the program really works.
We have explored how program works
but you got to consider the privacy issue
before working on the actual project.
If your app is going to
violate some privacy issues,
then your application will be useless
after spending a whole month to build one.
This is all about ownership of each post
and is like a question,
can they be exposure
without any permission or something?
Fortunately, everything publicly posted
can be shared without any
permission in Facebook,
that is the policy.
This is not a great thing to know about
as an individual Facebook user,
but it may be nice to
know as an app developer.
TensorFlow Korea is a public group
and everything in it is also public,
so there were no problems at all
to launch this newsletter service.
I have found the supporting documents
through Facebook's Help
page and also I have found
some attorneys from the
US have confirmed it.
So please check the privacy issue
before diving into the implementation
unless your group is based on Facebook.
I'll skip over this slide a bit,
but it shows how to port this project
for your own community.
So it looks like there are
too many things to configure.
But actually, the only things
that should be modified
are information about your Facebook group.
You cannot avoid from this,
no matter what you're going
to build for Facebook,
is a total necessary step.
Even though, you're going to
build some other application
for Facebook other than
this newsletter service.
Like Facebook group ID, Facebook
app ID, application secret
also you should include
SMTP related information
to send email to somebody.
You don't really need to
modify the source code at all though,
if you don't wanna make any change,
like email design or parsing logic.
However, if your group
is not based on Facebook,
you should probably
modify the parsing logic,
requests and logics and et cetera.
Also, you've got to find out the way
you can request, post the
information to the server.
Maybe there should be some APIs
or you could build your own web crawler.
I'll recommend to do it so though.
So this project has been on service
for the last two months or so.
We have reached more than
500 subscribers in a month,
and I think yes
it is still not small number,
but not bad as the first attempt.
I assume many members still not even
aware of existence of this service.
I am planning to improve
newsletter service
by applying deep learning in near future.
This pipeline shows a simple MLOps
which is like DevOps for
machine learning project.
The core idea is to classify
each post into categories
like research, news,
Q&A, tools and et cetera,
by leveraging NLP model like BERT.
It is to avoid some post
with not much helpful information
to be included in the newsletter.
Because the current system grab everything
without knowing what categories they are,
so for example,
some events like sharing out
newly published books are
sometimes included as the top one rank.
I think this kind of information
is not real important to anyone
if the event has been closed already.
Leveraging NLP model is a trivial job,
I can just make and deploy
one useless model easily.
However, since the characteristics of post
on a community gets evolved
and changed over time,
the model should be retrained
to avoid to be outdated.
So DVC and CML are simple,
but nice projects to tackle this problem.
With DVC, which stands
for Data Version Control,
you can manage versions of data.
But data here doesn't mean
the training data only,
but it also can support the management
of versioning deep learning model.
Actually, it can manage everything
that is too large to be
stored in GitHub repository.
It manages the version of
file which is actually stored
in Google Drive or storage platform,
you will also need to keep meta information
and a GitHub repository.
That's the only requirement to achieve
this data version controlling stuff.
CML is continuous machine learning,
is not thing but to
report training results
with a set of rich information like graph
as a GitHub PRs command.
Based on this report, we can
decide whether to merge the PR.
So when new data arrives, it
will trigger GitHub Action
to train a model on a data.
After training is done,
the reports will be posted
as a GitHub PRs command via CML.
By looking at it, we can
decide to merge the PR,
and when it is merged, it'll
trigger another GitHub Action
to create new endpoint
for the most recently pretrained model.
The reason to make
everything work automatic is,
there is a chance that I 'll
quit the administrator position
at TensorFlow Korea
community at some point.
When it happens, I won't
hand this project over to someone else,
and let him or her to manage
this project with a minimal effort.
Or hopefully no one should
really look much in details
or not a human being involved at all.
If you find yourself being
interested in this project,
please find it by searching my ID,
deep dash diver in GitHub.
There are lots of contribution points.
And I need help, and thank you.
Thanks for listening,
I hope this presentation
has given you a valuable information.
Thank you for listening a lot.
See you.