This is James.
You can also call me Ing Wei
The title of my session is Honey,
Python inside Android is under control!
First of all, let me introduce myself.
MY, of course, you know
that my name is James
and I am the chair
for PyCon Malaysia 2019.
I'm also the co-chair
for PyCon Malaysia 2018.
And also,
I'm a senior automation engineer
in one of the leading
industrial insurance company,
where my daily job is to deal
with the network automations
and discovery for network
devices in the company.
Just a small information
about PyCon Malaysia,
currently PyCon Malaysia has about 100--
size of 100 people of the community, so we
are quite a small community at this time.
But right now, our growth rate has
quite steadily increased.
We have also hosted
PyCon APAC 2020 online.
Even though the hosting
is quite difficult,
but I think at the time that
this has been recorded,
I believe that we have hosted
a very successful event.
Now, before we talk about the ideas
of the Android phone,
let us just look at how things
have been developed over 20 years.
On the left, it was the computer
that I had when I was 15 years old.
It was for 486-DX4 with the CPU speed
about 100 MHz. The RAM is 8MB.
And if you look at the size and the OS
has been low there compared to today,
certainly you might say that this is very sad
and it can't do much during the time.
But that was the computer that I had
during the time when I was 15 years old,
compared to the current
phone that I have right now.
Current phone that I have right now,
I have the RAM which is more than 2GB
which is about 8GB and the hard disk
size is about more than 8GB.
probably we have more than 16,
and the size compared to it
is about a pocket size. Okay?
Even though it runs on the Android or iOS,
but the OS that owns by our phone
runs much more powerful than what I
had 15 years ago, which is DOS 6.22.
because the OS nowadays is a 64-bit
of the operating system.
Meanwhile, 20 years back, I have
only 16-bit of operating system,
which is DOS 6.22.
So, our Android phone nowadays
is not just a phone.
It is also a computer
and has a lot of sensors.
And these sensors help us to track a
lot of things, for example, our locations,
the SLR meters. And then some of that
also equates with NFC
and a lot, a lot of different kinds of
apps that act as a tracker to track
not just our location, also our
health and everything.
But even though this Android
phone is very powerful nowadays,
we find that the phones will be
degraded on average of two years,
meaning that we need to change
the phone over two years.
So, if you look at the lifecycle
of your phone,
you find that every two years
you're going to have a new phone.
So, what are we going to do
with the old phones then?
So, the possibility of the old phones will
be either we throw it away after two years.
Or probably we'll just
keep it somewhere that we no longer see.
Or probably will just use it
for the sake of other apps.
Like I heard about there are some
people who use a particular GPS apps
on the old Android phone.
Or perhaps we'll give the phones
to our parents, who is not quite tech--
who is not quite good in using the tech.
And probably the last option will be what
as developers or programmers we’ll say,
Can we program it? Okay?
So, in this case, when we talk
about programming,
of course, we have a lot of options
like we do have Java, we do have Kotlin
and not to mention there are
some of the latest software
which is like Flutter I know that we
can definitely program that.
But somehow having a program on
the Android phone is not straightforward.
And to me,
all these languages are difficult to learn
in the sense that it has quite a big
challenge in terms of the learning steps.
So, this is what this talk
about, because what I'm thinking doing
in this project over here, is try
to run Python on Android phone.
And what I got as a feedback
of that is, people will say,
Well, you definitely can run the Python
on Android phone,
but are you able
to interact with the sensors?
Meaning that let's say if we want to
use a location,
are we able to attract or receive
the GPS location from the Android phone.
So, that is the question that I have.
Fortunately, I will say yes to my project
and the Python running on the Android can
do far more things that we can think of.
So, this is what the talks is about
and also this is also the motivation
of this project over here.
Now, what started the motivation
of this project is--
I still like my old phones, which is
having a very large RAM,
which is about 4 GB of RAM even
though I have used it for two years,
which you know, in hours, in what we
mentioned just now it’s kind of old,
but it's still running fast.
So, I would like to keep this phone
and learn how to write a Python
programming on this phone over that.
So, I decided to run a project called--
project for this which-- I would
like to run simple barcode scanner.
Because barcode scanner seems to be
quite expensive back in four years’ time.
So, I decided to say, okay,
is it possible for us to just
run a very simple Python code that
allows me to interact with the camera
on the Android phone so that it
can be used as a barcode scanner.
So, I decided to look for Google. Okay?
And this is what I got from Google.
So, turns out Google is always
your best friend. So, do utilize that.
So, the first search that I have
over that is Android barcode scanner
in six lines of Python code.
That turns out to be interesting.
And digging further, we find that the code
is really easy.
What I need to do is I just need to import
the library, import for Android,
and I just need to call the method.
Then I can scan the book,
scan the barcode of the book, and I
can get the information of the book.
So, this project has helped me a lot
because I have quite a number of books,
about 500 books at home.
So, cataloging the books has always
been a very painful job for me.
So, with this barcode
scanner using the Python,
it will definitely help me to
catalog my books easily without going
to enter the information
about the books one by one.
So, question over that, yes, can we
actually run or access
the sensors on the
phone using Python?
The answer is yes.
But how can we do that?
So, after that project, after that
project, I decided to dig further
and see what has offer in Python
on the Android phone.
Okay?
What I found out from that is, of course,
a few Python apps have been written,
but most of it can only run Python
interpreter, meaning that there's not much
Python app that can access
the sensors on the phone.
So, after a very long search,
I found out that there's one
app that allows me to do that.
Okay?
That will be the app that I'll review
at the end of the slide from that.
So, the first thing that I would like to
explore further on the Python of that is,
okay, since every phone has
an accelerometer,
meaning that the sensors
that measures the gravity,
so this is a very simple code that I write
for the Python on Android.
First thing, just get the gravity so I'll
record the time and after 120 seconds,
which is two minutes later,
I'll try to read the values of that.
So, if you look at the code
carefully, that actually reads
the gravitational field
from three different axes, X, Y, and Z,
and then I'll do an average of that.
So, that will give me the value of the G.
So, it is a very simple app that I
can write using Python on Android,
but that does not stop me to go
further because I would like to know
more about what happens at
the back end of this Python on Android.
So, I'll begin to look at that.
A few questions over here.
How does the Python
access an Android API?
How accurate is the data
that returns from the API?
And throughout the diggings
of these questions over there,
there was two files that I found out
from their repository,
which is one, androidhelper.py and
another one is android.py.
Okay. This is a small snippet
of the code for androidhelper.py.
So, they have different
kinds of methods over that
and of course, we would like to focus on
one method that we are very familiar with,
which is scanBarcode.
Throughout the reading
of the code for scanBarcode,
we'll realize that there's one part
of a very interesting method over that,
which is a private method in
this context, which is rpc scanBarcode.
So, does it mean that Python code
actually interacts
with Android API via rpc?
Okay, that's the first question.
And the second question is,
if rpc has been used,
how does it interact
with the intent or Android API?
So, since we mentioned that, the second
file that we look at, which is android.py,
then we'll begin to look
at that for android.py.
So, for the structures of android.py,
the class android is very simple.
First thing, you initiate the android
object or instance in this case,
and then your phones are
self-socket connection.
So this socket connection
will connect to its own local host
and then it'll you use the JSON data
to write the data to the Android API
via the rpc method. So, if you look
at the rpc method of that, you find that
there's a change--
that the data is being
is being changed to JSON format and it
will send the data to the Android API
via the socket easily.
So once the socket has
received and processed the data,
it'll return the result object over here.
So, it is quite simple for us to know how
things work at the back end of that.
So, as a summary-- oh, sorry, not
summary here.
On the Android end,
what happens is Android will receive
it via the rpc again, and it'll process it
according to the code’s intent and returns
the result as what we have seen
over here as a return of the result.
So, to summarize that,
what we see over there is,
when we write a python
script over there, first thing, we have
to import the android.helper once
this android.helper has been called,
it will send a request to the Android.
So android.py over here will process
your request and-- process the request
and send the JSON data to the intent
via the localhost socket.
The Android intent receive the request
then you will process and it'll receive
the data from the designated sensors.
For example, in this case where android.py
receive a request for scanBarcode,
it will process and send it via
the rpc and then opens up the camera.
The camera will scan the barcode
and process the data from the barcode
and send the data back to Android
and then to the Android and back
to the androidhelper and hence our screen
over there are able to read the data
from the barcode.
This is something that is quite
straightforward without that,
and looking at it, the API itself, it
is very elegant in a way that it is simple
and it does the job that it
needs to be done.
So, these are the APIs that currently
can be accessed, which is first thing,
as I keep mentioning, Accelerometer,
and we do have a Gyroscope.
In terms of in this word, some
of you prefer to call it orientation
and we do have Location, and we
can access Wi-Fi, Bluetooth, SMS,
phone calls, and everything.
However, there's few versions that
you can find for this Python on Android.
First thing, if you are downloading
from the Play Store, you might have
a limited privilege, but if you download
it from GitHub, then you have more access
to different kinds of the intent
or sensors on the phone.
So, as I mentioned before, there's
a few apps that you can use
rather-- other few other kinds of apps
that you have on the Google Play Store.
These are the two apps that I recommend
for you to play with, particularly
for the QPython3, because these are
the apps that allows you not just to write
a simple patent script for the
latest version, it allows you to run
the NumPy, SciPy, Scythe, as well
as the QRS together with android.py
as we mentioned before.
So, this is something
that works for you to try
and not to mention that this is an open
source app, meaning that if you know Java,
you can contribute your
Java code to this project.
So, purely this is an open
source project over there.
Okay. So, right now,
we have a demo time.
So, these are the demo.
So, the first demo, we'd like to do a
location tracking and for this demo
over there is a demo that shows
how we can read the data straight away
from the phone and display it with
a Leaflet via the Flask applications.
The purpose of this recording is to show
how the location tracking web app
works using the WebSocket
from the Python on Android.
So from this app over here what we can see is
the web app that we've wrote in Flask
connected to the WebSocket
which is the IP address of the WebSocket server
on the Python on Android app.
While the front-end is written using the vue.js
together with the Leaflet map app.
So, as you can see this is the code
that we have over there
where we connect to the WebSocket
and then we displayed it.
So, this is the web app that we see from there.
So it can get the current location
as what we can see over here
as well as getting the real-time GPS feed.
So right now we can get the feed.
Just wait for a while.
Okay, just try to refresh that
so that we get the location.
So, get the location,
and then we'll get the feed.
So right now, this feed is a little bit off
because right now I'm actually at the location
where has a quite bad Internet connection
so it will get an approximate location for that.
So it will have a little bit of deviation for that.
So meanwhile in this recording,
I'm going to record down
the location of this GPS live feed
for a good 10 minutes.
(Recording the location while moving)
Okay, as you can see,
I have stopped somewhere right now
to finish the recording.
So if you look at the trace,
it actually shows the driving I had at each point.
So if you click on all this point over there,
it shows you the time
where I drive, how I drive, and then the time.
So this drive over there also shows the speed,
of the speed of the location that I'm at,
as well as the plot.
So this is a clearly a very good demo
to show how I can track
the driving of myself as well as others, too,
by using just a very simple Python on
Android app.
Hope you enjoyed it.
Thank you.
So this is the demo for the location tracking.
Now, we like to look at another very fun
demo as well that we utilize the phone call.
So, in most of our data center for SRE,
we do have problems
with what we call as self-one,
or somebody calls that P1.
Okay? Meaning that you
have severity one,
means that you have an incident that
is really down, or you have some sort of
utilization, which goes
beyond your critical level,
which-- you need to address that.
What happens in this demo of that is
I'll generate a random number
to simulate the utilization of the CPU.
So, when the CPU usage is more than 80%,
I'll make my phone to call the SRE.
So, in this demo over there I
used a few ingredients over there,
which is the ZMQ.
In this case,
ZMQ is just Zero Message Queuing,
together with a simulator
CPU utilization tools, okay?
And also the Android call.
So, I'd like to begin
my demo of that.
The purpose of this demo
over here is to show that
we can use Python on Android
to write a simple call script
when we are having an issue
in the data center.
For example, in this demo over here,
we use the case of when the CPU is
hitting a percentage of 80 percent
the script will make a phone call
to the respective SRE.
So in this script over here,
this script actually is a very simple script
that allows me to send the incident
by using a random number generator.
So, first, in this case, I'm going to
generate the status of the CPU
by using a random number
from 0 to 100.
So if the CPU is hitting 80%,
we'll record the time, and then
it starts to send a string of '1'
to the respective ZMQ
on the IP address
which is as the following over here.
If the CPU is below 80%,
then we'll send a string of '0' over here.
So '1' over here represents the incident is happening,
which is the status that the CPU is hitting
a percentage of 80%,
while '0' is it's below 80%.
So for every five seconds,
we'll check
and if there's an incidence of that
we are going to send this across.
So right now, I'm going to start with
the script that I have.
What I'll do right now is
I'll start the script for now.
(Running the script)
And here I'm going to
show you the phone
I will start a video and then
I'll make the phone.
So if you look at the screen
I have a phone over here.
(Script is running)
We are still waiting because
the CPU has not reached above 80%.
Okay, it starts making a call.
(Bell rings)
Yep, if you hear that that is the sound.
So the phone is ringing right now.
(Bell rings)
So we are successfully making a call.
Okay, so right now,
it's again, made a call in short while.
Let's just wait for a moment.
Okay, it's going to make a call again.
(Bell rings)
Okay, the phone's ringing, Okay.
Yep, the phone is ringing so...
Okay, so answer the phone.
So here comes the demo.
Okay, here comes the demo.
So I hope you enjoyed the demo
for this script over here.
Thank you.
So these are the reference for my project.
If you like or if you're interested,
you can look at this, all these
reference of that,
so that you can get more details on that.
With that, that is my presentation
and thank you for
attending my presentation.
Thank you.