I'm Julin Shaji, and my talk is
Publishing Well-Formed Python Packages.
Hi, welcome to my talk:
Before we begin, let me say,
the source of the images that I have
used in this presentation are linked
to the images themselves in the slides.
We can share the link
for the slides later on.
So, what do I mean by
a well-formed package?
A package that has attained some sort of
a structure by adhering to some guidelines
and practices, which
makes it easier to work with,
and makes collaborating with others
on the project a more fruitful experience.
Making changes to such a
package is a less likely to be chaotic.
It can be adapted to match
the changing requirements
with significantly less effort.
But how is it possible?
How can we make
our project better formed?
Sufficient documentation,
test, and readability
are some of the key factors in this.
A good first step towards making your
package well-formed is
by adopting a coding style
and by using linting tools.
It's good to have the suggestions
mentioned in step eight in mind.
Consistent formatting has a significant
impact on the readability of your code.
This will help us weed out
a lot of bugs as it can make
bug-inducing code snippets more prominent
so that it will catch your attention
and all that other tools that we use and
you will be able to attend to it faster.
But it should be noted that PEP8 itself
says that its suggestions should be
taken more as guideline
rather than as steadfast rules.
This is probably applicable for the
coding style that you adopt as well.
For example, consider a long link
that you have in your code as a sort of
reference to some website,
possibly in a comment or something
and your code coding style specifies
a line length limit of say 80 characters.
And if your link is way
beyond 80-character limit,
instead of us splitting that link into two
lines or something,
it's probably better
to create an exception
and make an exception
for your coding style
so that it will remain a single link,
and whatever editor that you're using
can still recognize it as a link, so that
it can go directly to that link by just
clicking on it instead of first joining
them together or pasting it or whatever.
Pylint and flake8 are among the
prominent linting and style tools
used in Python packages.
Both are very much configurable.
Although the default configuration
can be used as a good
starting point in your project.
And then there's Black.
If you don't want to spend too
much time fixing and formatting all
all your code all the time and don't mind
letting an external tool take control of--
take your code formatting
part, you can use Black.
It is becoming more
and more popular these days.
It can automatically reformat
your code for you so that
regardless of the style that
you use to write your code--
that you use to actually write your
code, after applying Black on it,
it will just look the same
as Black outputs it.
This is often helpful if a lot of people
are collaborating together on your project
and you want all
the code to look the same.
Another mechanism that can
help is static type checking.
Python has been supporting type
annotation for quite some time now.
Making use of it not only
improves the readability of your code
without having any effect
on the code execution part
but it also enables us
to run static type checks.
In a way, we can have the advantage of a
statically typed system in Python as well.
These checks often help to reveal
certain subtle bugs that would be
very difficult to
figure out otherwise.
Mypy, pytype and pyre are some of the
prominent static type checking tools
available in Python
we have right now.
Let us use an example to illustrate the
advantage of mypy in type annotations.
I have a function here named add.
Not a good name, but
which accepts two arguments; X and Y.
If X Boolean value is true, it
returns the value of Y as such.
Otherwise, it adds 10 to Y and returns it.
But looking at this we have no
idea what kind of values X and Y are.
Here I have passed two integers
as arguments to the function.
But X could be a Boolean, a list
or anything. It could be anything,
no matter what we pass
through it, it could be anything.
So, we have no idea what the correct
argument should be, and as of now,
we have no mechanism to check it as well.
Contrast it with the version
that we have on the right side.
Just by looking at it, we can say
that X is a Boolean, Y is an integer
and the function has returns int.
Right?
See what a difference it made.
It's a lot more readable.
Don't you agree?
And running mypy on this example,
in the updated example
that we have on the right
side would lead to this error.
Argument one should have been
a bool and instead, we got an int.
So mypy can catch such kind of-- I
mean, it could happen by mistake the
stuff like this.
Mypy can easily catch them.
And usually the outcome of these bugs
you'll experience only when actually--
actually executing this program.
But mypy can do that without
even executing it, it’s static.
Another concern is dead code.
As a project evolves, it's bound to have
some dead code accumulated along with it.
This dead code could interfere with
the rest of the code,
and can lead to unexpected results
because of this interference.
We can use tools to help us identify
dead code so that it may be removed.
Vulture is such a tool.
It does static analysis to figure
out which objects may be unused
and reports it along
with its confidence score,
how confident it is that
that object is unused.
Vulture is quite fast as it doesn't
need to actually execute all the code,
but identifies the unused parts using
Python’s abstract syntax tree
Before mentioning unit testing,
let us talk about a project’s layout,
its directory structure.
Two of
the most commonly seen structures
used by the Python project
are the flat layout and the src layout.
The flat layout, as you can see,
has the source code and the test
in the same directory level. In this
case, the source code is mentioned--
is inside the package name directory
and the test in the test directory.
But the src layout adds a nesting to the
directory and adds another directory level
for it to store the source code.
Usually the name of the outer
directory is src and within which
the source code is provided
inside another directory.
But that said, there is no
officially recommended layout for--
when choosing a layout for your project.
You may choose a layout
that fits your need better.
Check out these links to see some interesting
arguments regarding project layout.
Now comes unit testing.
Of course, it's important to check if your
code works as you expect it to work.
Otherwise, there'd be no point, right?
So, but for the sake of unit testing,
it is helpful to design the code so that
different functionalities, the
major functionality, are divided into--
into separate testable functions.
There are a lot of testing and tools
and frameworks available for Python.
Among them is the building unit test
and the third party pytest,
which is widely used.
So, let us consider a simple
example to illustrate the use of testing.
I have here a simple function str_cmp,
which takes two strings: str1 and str2;
finds the ratio of the lengths and
returns a Boolean based on that ratio.
Here I have on the right side
the test that I have
written for this tiny function.
Had string values and the
expected return values specified using
the parameterize from pytest.
And once I ran it, I got the error
that I have shown in the bottom side.
So, I got a ZeroDivisionError.
So, why is that?
Because if the value, if the second
string, the str true string’s value
is an empty string and the division
will here be divide by zero division,
so it will lead to error.
I had not considered that
while writing that function,
and writing appropriate test cases let
me know that if there's something wrong.
That there’s something
that I had not considered earlier
when I wrote the function.
So, I will be able to fix that
because now I’ve come across that
in the testing phase itself.
If I had not done the testing, I
would have given it out to others
and they would have come
back to me with complaints, right?
Yes. Something like that.
But writing test cases
alone is not enough.
We should know that tests that we have
written cover all the cases.
I mean, all the desired parts of code
should be covered,
otherwise there would be little
point in writing the test, right?
So that's where test coverage comes in.
100% coverage is ideal and desirable,
but it may not always be possible.
There are some projects, for example,
Welcher that we mentioned earlier
has almost 100% coverage.
But that is not always
possible due to various reasons.
So, coming to tools that can be
used to measure test coverage,
there is coverage.py,
a standalone package,
and there's also pytest-cov,
a plugin for the pytest module
that we discussed earlier.
Both are quite popular.
Let us consider another simple example.
We have a function, foo, which accepts
an integer and returns a Boolean.
So, it basically returns true if
the number is an even number,
otherwise a false is returned.
But note that my test case covers
only the even part; the odd part,
the condition
where the function foo accepts
an odd number is not actually tested.
So running coverage in such
a situation will give you this--
this output that you see on the right-hand
side, they say coverage is only 75%,
three lines were run, one is missing.
And the missing line is
highlighted in the red background.
The coverage can generate STM reports,
so this is the output
that I got from that.
But once I fix that and I write-- update
my test to cover the old input as well,
I run coverage again.
Now it says 100% coverage.
So, now we have a lot of tests
to run on the package, right?
From Pyland, to MyPy, Welcher,
pytest, so a lot of tests to run,
a lot of checks to be run on your package.
So, we can definitely use a test
automation tool to run all these tests.
And also, we need to test on
all the supported Python versions
and Python implementations, so we can
maybe your package is designed to run on
even on PyPi another
implementation, not seed pyth,
and maybe if you
need to verify that your
package works on all the
supported Python versions.
Maybe suppose that you used the walrus
operator, which is available only on--
from Python 3.8 onwards on your project
and you want your project to support
even on Python 3.6.
So, you are unaware
that you actually used the walrus operator
and you run the tox test, I
mean the test automation test
and you will find that you have
an error in 3.6, but not on 3.8,
so you will know what to do.
Tox and Nox are some of the prominent test
automation tools that we have in Python.
So, the test automation tools can be used
to run the test locally or maybe even with
other continuous integration services
that you use, whichever ones that you use.
Remember what I mentioned about
the possibility of flat layer packages
running into problems while testing?
Well, that's because tools like
tox create virtual environments just
to run your tests so that they are
tested just like they were installed
like in your user machine.
But if you had a flat environment,
the source code itself could be imported
from the test instead of the package
that you have had installed in the virtual
environment that the tox or any other test
automation tool like that created for you.
But such layout doesn't have
this problem as the source code itself
cannot be directly imported
from the test directory,
because it's inside yet
another directory level.
So, that eliminates the
possibility of an accidental import
like-- that is possible in a flat layout.
Once you have your project ready,
you can build and package it so that
you can share your work
with others and let them use it.
The build process would create files
that can be used to install your package
in other machines, like
the wheel file, for example.
There are several tools these days
that can be used to package your project.
Like setuptools from PyPA,
the Python Packaging Authority,
or the newer non-PyPA
tools like flit and poetry.
The next step after packaging
a project is publishing it.
If you're using setuptools, you can
use the twine package to upload it to
the server of your preference.
In the case of flit and poetry, they
can do the publishing by themselves.
People commonly upload
their packages to the pyPI server.
But if you are publishing there
before trying the actual pyPI server,
you can try out the test pyPI server,
which is a place to try out your package
and see if all is well before
publishing to the actual pyPI.
Other than the tools that I've mentioned
so far, there are a lot of other tools
that you can use to-- that can be
used to make your package better.
For example, there's
bumpversion, which can be used to
change your Python package’s version.
And there's precommit, which can be
used to run commands before committing,
isort to sort your imports
and your Python source files,
and cookiecutter, especially
handy if you're using setuptools
to start your project.
Once you have your package ready tests
all set up you could use a CI/CD
to run the test automatically.
You can even, depending on
the CI/CD service or tools that you use,
you can even view
the results of the past test and all,
which can be quite helpful.
Now, due to some proposals that have
been accepted by the PyCon community,
the pyproject.toml file has become
the center point of the Python packages.
Earlier, it used to be just setuptools.
Now you can actually choose your build
system to be something else if you like.
Because of the toml file
involved, you can probably expect--
we can probably expect a toml
module inside the Python language
standard library itself,
because a lot of projects will need that
to pass pyproject.toml files’ content.
Most of the packages
that I have mentioned,
those packages’ configuration
files used to be separate,
so there'll be a different
configuration file for each tool.
It used to be like that, but a lot of
such tools have moved their configuration
part to the pyproject.toml file.
You can configure the tool
in the appropriate section
within the toml file itself.
While some projects are yet to make the
move,
we can expect them to make that move
in the near future.
So, we have come to the
end of the presentation.
So a quick recap of what we saw.
We talked about the linting.
We talked about static type checking.
Dead code identification, testing,
and test coverage and test automation
and the packaging part.
Follow the practices
promoted by these tools
and your project is
bound to be better formed.
Thanks for being here.