Bring your Python script to more users, Nikkie
Nice to meet you everyone.
Please call me Nikkie.
I'm participating from Japan.
Thank you for the
opportunity to speak online.
I use the ID @ftnext
on Twitter and GitHub.
I'm working on Natural Language
Processing at Uzabase in Tokyo.
I'm enthusiastic to automate
boring stuff with Python.
I've been a staff of PyCon JP
since last year.
In this summer, I've been speaking
online at PyCons around the world.
I talked about this topic
at EuroPython in July.
And I speak on another topic;
How to automate PyCon JP staff activities
at PyCon Africa.
Let's cut to the chase.
Why am I telling you:
Bring your Python script to more users?
After reading a first Python book,
you can write a Python script
to automate the boring stuff.
It's beneficial to have
Python do the boring stuff for me.
Your Python script should help
others who have similar boring stuff.
In this talk, I will share how to
bring your useful script to others.
I'm glad if you try one of what I
introduce after your first Python book.
This talk is a quick tour.
I will share three implementations
to convert your Python
script for others to use.
Three implementations are
CLI app, GUI app, and Web app.
What kind of boring stuff
am I talking about in this talk?
This talk deals with resizing images
to a smaller size
as an example of boring stuff.
I have lots of images
of varying sizes.
I want to resize all images to fit
in 300 pixels square, keeping the ratio.
For example, the image on the
left is longer with the height.
So, resize this image to width
of 300 pixels, and keeping the ratio.
Resizing them small by hand one by one
is tedious. So, automate it with Python.
I wrote a script, shrink_image.py
referring a first Python book.
To operate images from Python,
I use Pillow package.
I put all the images in one directory,
use pathlib
to find the path of the images
in the directory one by one.
In resize image function,
open the image with path
and calculate new size to keep the ratio.
Then, resize the image and save it.
This function returns true if
and only if it resizes the image.
I put all the images in
img_pyconjp directory.
Script shrink_image.py
resizes images in that directory.
After execution, I get a directory
with images of smaller sizes.
We are ready for the main talk.
Our first stop in this quick tour
is CLI, Command Line Interface.
There is an issue with the
current script. It is hard-coded.
The target directory is hard-coded in
the script, so we need to edit the script
to target a different directory.
To resolve the issue, we modify the script
to specify the target directory
from the command line.
Specify from the command line.
So, this is CLI.
There is no need to edit the
script every time you run it.
There are several ways to do it.
But I'd like to introduce argparse
from Python standard library.
Let's look at an example code
that introduces argparse.
In the first line,
import ArgumentParser from
argparse, then create a parser
add argument to the parser
and parse arguments.
That's all you need.
The four lines allow the script to take
arguments from the command line.
So, name attribute, so args.name is the
value we specified in the command line.
So, I show two examples
on the above example.
Now we need to specify some
value as name from the command line.
If a name is not specified,
help message is displayed.
In the example below,
if you pass PyConKorea
as a name argument,
the script prints a message;
Hello, PyConKorea.
It's time to modify shrink_image.py.
Import ArgumentParser
and create parser.
Then code add_argument and parse_args.
The hard code observed target
directory has been removed.
The target directory is now
specified from the command line.
We don't need to change
anything else. It's easy.
In running the script, you can pass
here you can pass the directory
where the image is located
from the command line.
The script resizes images in the directory.
We do not need to edit
the script every time running it.
Next we will brush it up on this CLI app.
We brush up the script to specify the
maximum length from command line.
The maximum length was set
or hard-coded at 300 pixels.
We will be able to specify this.
Are you getting used
to seeing this ArgParse code?
The point is a double hyphen in
add argument.
Here, double hyphen.
Arguments that start with
double hyphen are optional to specify.
Arguments without
double hyphen are required
and the specified order is important.
This example shows two parameters
of the add Argument result.
If you do not specify
the type parameter here,
entered value from the command
line is converted as an integer.
The default parameter
specifies default value.
If you do not specify max length from
the command line, it will be 300 pixel.
Let's run the updated CLI app.
In this time, we
specified --max_length 200.
Images have been resized
to smaller sizes than before.
Here is a tip to make
the CLI app easier to use.
We will be surprised
when you see the traceback--
traceback when you
type an incorrect path.
The path does not point to any directory.
So the script raises file not found error.
To prevent this, specify a
function to type parameter here
in add_argument method.
A function, existing_path, converts
string value into path object.
After creating a path object from a
string value check if the path points
points to an existing file or directory.
This is code for check.
If not, it raises exception
ArgumentTypeError.
We updated the script to prevent
the user from seeing the traceback.
There are no tracebacks.
I introduced argparse to you.
Argparse allows you to specify
arguments from the command line.
There is no need to edit the script.
About add_argument method, required
arguments result here heading--
result heading double hyphen and optional
arguments with heading double hyphen
Using type parameter add_argument,
convert string value specified
in the command line to other types.
To learn CLI more,
please visit the appendix.
Our second stop in this quick
tour is GUI, Graphical User Interface.
You can now create
your CLI app with argparse
Everything has strengths and weaknesses.
Developers are familiar with CLI apps,
but non-developers might
not be familiar with them.
I want non-developers to use the app.
Let's think about how to make
the app more user-friendly than CLI.
Now, it's GUI's turn.
There are many, many GUI apps on PCs.
GUI apps should be more familiar and
user friendly to non-developers than CLI.
In this part, we will convert the CLI app
to a GUI app, like the right image.
Users can specify a
path to the target directory
and the max length on the screen.
I will show you a demo.
Users enter paths of the target directory
and max lengths.
So, in this case, I paste target directory
and max length is 200.
Then quick resize.
So, this CLI app shows
resized images here.
The directory includes two images,
and two images are resized now.
So, I introduced the demo app from now.
There are several packages to build
GUI apps, but I'd like to introduce Eel.
Eel could make it easier
to implement GUI apps.
Note that to use the Eel package, Google
Chrome needs to be installed on your PC.
A GUI app made with Eel
has four components.
One, of course, is a Python code,
and I will explain, HTML and JavaScript.
They are essential for the
Eel app, and CSS is optional.
So, if you want to know,
visit the appendix slides.
HTML is code written
using tags like upper right.
It defines the
structures of GUI apps.
Google Chrome shows the input
field comes first and the button next.
If you want to learn more visit this link.
JavaScript adds interaction to GUI apps.
For example,
when a user clicks the button,
JavaScript changes the screen
by rewriting certain tags in the HTML.
The critical difference with Python
code is that JavaScript requires
‘let’ keyword before a variable name.
the keyword let is very easy to forget
because I am enthusiastic Pythonista,
but JavaScript doesn't
work well without let keyword.
The same goes for the
trailing semi-colons as well.
This is a key point.
Eel allows you to call functions with—
call functions written in
Python from JavaScript.
This allows you to convert a
Python script into a GUI app
with just a little HTML
and a little JavaScript.
If you want to learn
JavaScript more, visit this link.
The three components are arranged in
two files; a Python file and a HTML file.
In Eel’s way, a HTML file
is also placed in a folder called web.
JavaScript is written in the HTML file
because we write a written.
Let’s build a simple GUI app.
When you click the button,
this app displays a greeting,
“Hello World,” and
a random number.
I will share two things; how to execute
the process by clicking the button
and how to change the screen.
The directory structure
is the same as before,
one Python file and one
HTML file with JavaScript.
A Python function say_hello
returns, storing its greeting
message, Hello World,
and random number
such as one, two, three.
The point is the decorator, eel.expose.
JavaScript called functions
decorated with eel.expose.
eel.init and eel.start allow
to use hello.html under hello directory.
HTML consists of two parts; head and body.
In the head tag, you write JavaScript.
In the body tag, you write other
tags to define your structure.
I would define the greet
button under empty paragraph.
The paragraph has a id
greeting, JavaScript uses this id.
There is a button on the top of the screen
and below it there is an empty paragraph.
The point is attribute onclick
of the button tag.
This code means
when this button is clicked,
JavaScript function greeting is called.
The function greeting is called
when a user clicks the greet button.
It's a unique writing style here,
series or parentheses.
JavaScript first calls
say_hello function in Python file,
and then waits for the return value.
After receiving the return value,
JavaScript recalls print_greeting function
written in JavaScript, with the return
value of Python say_hello function.
This writing style of waiting for
a return value is called a call back.
The print_greeting function
operates on HTML tag ID greeting.
So, print_greeting can rewrite
the content of the empty paragraph.
When you code this function with
a message, hello world one,
the contents of the paragraph
changes to hello world one.
So, users see a greeting
after clicking the button. That’s it.
Now it's time to convert the
image size app to GUI app.
I will share how to handle input values.
You are getting used to arranging
the two files, Python file and HTML file.
We'll put the resized images in the
images directory and the web directory.
The Python code is the same as before.
Create a function, resize,
and decorate with eel.expose.
Now we can call it from JavaScript.
You can manipulate files on your
PC from Python, without restriction,
but from JavaScript
there is some restriction.
So, pass the directory path as the
user enters it and let Python operate it.
Resize function returns a restore
with the file path for each resized image.
In Java script, we use this list to
return to-- sorry, we use this
list to rewrite contents in HTML.
So, HTML defines fields
that the users can enter.
User can specify the target paths
and the max lengths on the screen.
Set the onclick attribute
of the resize button to recall
the JavaScript resize function.
When the resize function
over JavaScript is called,
it gets a target path and the maximum
lengths using the target’s IDs.
Then JavaScript calls the Python
resize function with the entered values
using call back
after waiting the list
return from resize function.
JavaScript calls it listUpImages function.
The listUpImages function rewrites
the HTML using a listUpImages path.
To display image in HTML
using the img tag here
in the source attribute
of the img tag specifies
the path to the image.
This needs to be a
relative path to resize HTML,
and the Python function
already returns a relative path.
listUpImages function writes some
img elements into the empty Div element.
So, users can see the
resized images on the screen.
You can distribute eel app.
Install PyInstaller,
then type this command
to create distributable binary.
Distributable binary is
created at dist directory.
In my case, from macOS to macOS.
Note that distribution requires
knowledge of PyInstaller.
In some cases,
distribution may not be easy.
I introduced Eel to you.
Eel has four components;
Python, HTML, JavaScript, and CSS.
Eel enables JavaScript
to code Python functions.
To execute the process by clicking a
button in HTML, set a JavaScript function.
To handle input and display
on the screen in JavaScript,
get the entered value
and rewrite the contents.
To learn GUI more,
please visit the appendix.
Our final stop in this quick tour
is web apps, web applications.
I’ll tell you again that everything
has strengths and weaknesses.
GUI apps are user-friendly
to non-developers,
but distribution is sometimes tough
because of OS dependency or some pitfalls.
GUI apps need to be installed.
So, some users may feel
installation is a bit difficult.
Can we avoid distribution
and installation?
Now it's web app style.
Once users connect to the internet,
the app is immediately
available, without installation.
Web apps have GUI and
it is easy to start using.
The web is a mechanism
for sharing information
and one of the ways we use the internet.
So, I will show you a demo,
and this is a browser window,
and I access to this link
to demo web app
and I choose images
and size, specify the size, so 300 pixels.
So, web app resize it and displays them.
So, I can download this one.
So demo is over.
I will introduce
how to create the demo app.
In CLI and GUI app parts, we are
thinking about a single machine.
In web app part we are
thinking of more than one machine.
Multiple machines can
be classified into two roles.
The server is a mechanism--
sorry,
the server is a machine
where the web app is running.
We put the source code on servers.
The client is a machine
that uses web apps.
For example, we use web apps via
browsers from PCs and smartphones.
This slide shows the communication
between the server and the client.
The client sends a request to a server.
The server runs a process
based on the request.
Once the process is completed, the
server returns the response to the client.
What's in the request and the response?
A request includes a URL,
a string started with
HTTPS or HTTP.
URL shows which server to access,
and which process on the server to call.
A request also includes
information entered into your browser.
The server processes the information.
A response includes HTML as a string.
Here is a good news: we can
recycle HTML files in the GUI path.
There are several packages to build web
apps, but I'd like to introduce Flask.
Flask could make it easier
to implement simple web apps.
A web app has four components.
I wish I could tell you all of them,
but this talk we'll only
deal with Python and HTML.
JavaScript and CSS are optional,
so not covered in this talk.
In Eel, JavaScript handles interactions,
but in a web app,
Python code in server handles them.
We’ll start with a simple example
to be familiar with Flask.
When you open the URL in your browser,
the app displays a greeting:
Hello World, with a random number.
The directory structure
is similar to Eel apps.
Create two files:
Python file and a HTML file.
By running the Python script,
you can start the server on your PC.
You can send a request to it
by opening this link.
When the user opens the URL in
the browser, it sends a request
and the request includes URL.
Once receives the request,
the server starts a process
corresponding to /hello.
After completing the process,
the server returns a response.
The browser receives the response
and render HTML on the screen,
so the user can see a greeting message.
In Python implementation, first, create
an instance of Flask and the variable.
App stores it.
The point is to decorate hello function
with app.route decorator.
This hello function processes all
requests to hello.
All requests to /hello.
The function gets a string
greeting by calling say_hello function,
and say_hello creates a-- sorry--
and hello function returns a
response by render_template function,
which creates a response
based on template’s HTML--
hello.html on the template directory
and this variable message.
Next, HTML implementation.
Flask's render_template function
can handle not only HTML, but
also Jinja2 template tags, uh this one.
Double curly brackets message
is one of the Jinja2 template tags.
This template tag is replaced
by the value of a variable in HTML.
When you pass the variable
message to the return--
sorry, to the render template function,
In the returned HTML, we do not
see double hyphen curly bracket.
Now, create image resize web app.
When you open the app’s
URL from your browser,
you’ll see a screen like the left image.
Specify images and lengths,
then click the send button.
The web app resizes the images
and displays them like the right image.
If a user doesn't specify an image,
the screen displays in the same way
as it does in the Hello World example.
So, send a request and process
and return response and render it.
How to handle images in web apps.
After the user specifies the image,
the client sends a copy
of the image to a server.
Request includes data or copy image.
So, web app loads the image from
data, resizes it and saves on the server.
We need to save the image at
public directory on the server.
img tag works for public
images on the server.
In-- Eel part-- about Eel part,
we've already used img tags, in fact,
Oh, sorry, we already used img tag.
So, this time we use the same img tag.
Put the resized image
in the images directory.
This directory will be published.
In Python code, the difference
between hello_world.py and
that is-- the difference is
static_folder parameter.
static_folder=”images”
publishes the images directory.
Images in the directory
can be displayed in HTML.
Resize function is decorated by
app.route /resize so it processes requests
including /resize URL.
When you open /resize in your
browser without sending any image data,
you will see the
following slide HTML.
Here, it's called in the body tag
and it defines input fields.
You can see input fields
to select images on your computer
and specify max lengths.
When an image and maximum lengths are
specified and the send button is clicked,
the data is sent to the same /resize path.
In this time, the condition of
the if statement becomes false.
So, code in this slide is executed.
Python receives a max_length on the image
file in the request sent by the browser.
After resizing the image data, save
it to the image directory on the server.
render_template function receives
a list of paths of resized images.
Render receives paths for
render_template function.
It creates a response based on
these template tags.
{ and % is run with Jinja2 template tags.
And as this is a false statement
in Python, this tag
behaves--
false statement. So, it creates
img tags for each image.
Users can see resized
images on their browsers.
Here’s how to use the
demo I mentioned earlier.
Several services allow you
to run your code as a web app.
To run your app on Heroku, install
gunicorn and create config files
and then push your code to Heroku.
Recap time.
Web app receives a request from
a client, and returns a response.
I introduced Flask to you.
Flask executes the Python function
corresponding to the
URL in the request.
Flask creates a response
using temporary tags.
In web apps, to display
the images in HTML,
you need to set images
to publish on the server.
So we use static_folder argument in Flask.
To learn web app more,
please visit the appendix.
Here's a recap of our tour.
In CLI, we resolve the hard-coded
by specifying from the command line.
GUI app is more user friendly and
easier for non-developers to use.
To build your GUI app, we write
HTML and the JavaScript, or we can--
we can use web apps; as you
connect to the internet no installation.
In web, we need to sync communication
with the server and the client.
In the server, Python
code processes sent data.
So, my talk is over.
Ah-- my last message is,
bring your script and
automate someone's boring stuff
with your Python script.
Thank you very much
for your attention.