Hello, thank you for having
me at PyCon Korea 2020.
It's truly my honor to
present the following topic;
Your Escape Plan
from Numpy and Cython.
Here is some of my information.
My name is Chen-Lin Yang
and you can find me on
GitHub C-L-Y-A-N-G.
I'm a Taiwanese
and live in Taipei now
Currently working for a cyber security
company called CyCraft Japan,
and I'm also a member of
the Machine Learning Team.
So basically, all my daily life is dealing
with millions of logs, generated by
a lot of endpoints
in different countries.
Okay, before we start, here's
one very quick question for you.
Let's say you have a very large Numpy
array, which contains a lot of floating
points and you want each element
to multiply itself eight times,
which of the following code do
you think will run faster?
Is it A, the power function of Numpy,
or B, X times times 8,
or C, the most naive one X times X,
and then repeat four times?
I'll give you three seconds
to think about it.
The answer might surprise you, is C, the
most naive one.
You just use X times X,
and then repeat four times.
In order to prove it, here's the result
of my benchmark code.
As you can see the power function
of Numpy and X**8.
They both took about two seconds
and therefore the most naive one
X*X repeat four times,
and then you can see
it only takes 0.4 seconds.
So, it's about five times faster
than previous two, but there is a case.
So, if, unless you are doing
the scientific computing,
which require very, very high accuracy,
otherwise the result of the last one
will be a very small difference
than the previous two.
The difference is like 10
to number of power, negative 20.
So, I believe in most case you will
just choose the final-- last solution,
X*X, and then repeat four times.
Okay. Let's move on.
Why not Cython?
If you ever have
the Numpy code performance issue
and ask your friends, colleagues,
or teachers, how to improve it,
the most likely the answer you will get
is like, “Why don't you try on Cython?”
So, in the slide, I will give some
pros and cons regarding to it.
First, let's take a look at
advantage. If you are using Cython
and of course you can utilize
a lot of 3rd party C libraries,
and normally C code runs much,
much faster than the Python code.
And also, Cython allows you to release
the Global Interpreter lock or code GIL,
which means that your market-rated program
can be run much, much
faster than the existing one.
And also you can still have the
run-time check for the common problem
like the boundary check or some
error handling, and which will be handled
by the upper layer Python.
And then last, the Cython
syntax is very similar to Python,
meaning that you can learn it
in a very short amount of time,
but also it has some disadvantage.
The first thing I can think is that you
have to handle the memory by yourself.
So, for example, if you are
using malloc in your Cython code,
and then you have to use this memory
by yourself and freely after all,
and you have to do it all by your own.
Otherwise it might cause some very
serious memory leak.
And also, to get the ultimate performance
with Cython, to write a C code
and the low level intrinsic cannot
be avoided.
So, no matter what,
if you want to get the best
performance, you have to write a C code.
And trust me, it's really
painful. It's just something like this.
And why do I know it? Because
the code you see is written by myself.
Great. Let's have a look
to today's example.
This example we'll use as a
benchmark for the rest of the talk.
So, let's have a look.
If you are not new to machine learning,
you must know what SoftMax function is.
The formula is just like the one
on the screen, and don't worry,
I'm not going to explain
it in a mathematical way.
All you have to know is that it's a number
divided by the sum of a lot of numbers
and that's enough.
And you might think the formula
itself looks very easy and it shouldn't be
very hard to implement in
Python. And yes, you are correct.
But if you try to implement with the
formula on this screen, you will easily
encounter a numerical problem.
In Computer Science, we call it
an underflow or overflow issue.
And on the next slide, I will
give you an underflow example.
So, to avoid this kind of situation,
a trick called the log-sum
exponential will be used.
Now here's the example of underflow.
Let's say the sum of this power
of the denominator is 134217728
and the last part is its reciprocal.
And what will happen if we
are trying to add them together?
Here's the benchmark code. As you
can see, I set variable A to 134217728
and then try to plus it with its
reciprocal and here's the result.
As you can see, it's exactly the
same as A. It's quite shocking, right?
This effect is called underflow.
You might think this
is not a very big deal,
but if you're doing a scientific
calculation, like Markoff Chan the input
data is a list of very small probability.
And just like my example, on the slide,
after a specific position, the
probability will not be counted,
which will cause a very large
error in your final result.
So, as I mentioned in the previous
page, this problem can be solved
by a simple trick called
LogSum Exponential,
and the formula is just like
the one I show on the slide.
And the result of this formula
will mathematically equivalent
to the softmax function.
And don't worry again, because
I'm not going to prove it in the talk,
but the answer can be
easily found on the internet.
So, in order to prove it-- it really
works, here is another example code.
As you can see the final result over here,
you can see the very little difference
between this one and the previous one.
So, the smaller value is not cut or
avoided, which will result in a more,
more accurate result
to your final answers.
Some of you might ask,
SciPy already has this function,
Why would you rebuild your own wheel?
The answer to that
is SciPy’s function is built
for general purpose usage,
meaning it will perform a lot of checks
to make sure input and output data
is well handled, but in a real-world
scenario, you know what your data is.
So, you can rewrite the
function based on your data
Not only you can remove a lot
of checks but also it gives you
an opportunity to apply
third party boosting solution
to improve your code performance.
Today's case, I will assume
there's the input data will be only
one-dimensional array, and then I will
try to apply a three different solution
to the example I just mentioned before.
Okay, let's moving on.
How do we implement
LogSum Exponential in Numpy?
As I mentioned before, all my input
data will just be one dimensional array.
So, LogSum Exponential
can be implemented as follows.
As you can see, it only took three lines
of code to finish. It's quite easy right?
Here. I'm going to leave five
seconds to you to view the code.
Time is up.
So, after finish our
own version in NumPy,
I wrote a very simple benchmark
code to compare our own version versus
SciPy's original function.
The result is on the right.
As you can see, our version
is about 0.5 second faster
than the original SciPy's function.
You might think it's only 0.4 second,
it's not a lot.
But if you need to code
this function a million times a day,
it will save you
about half million seconds.
That's quite a lot right?
Starting from here, I'm going
to introduce three different types
of solutions that might improve
your Numpy performance.
The first solution will be CuPy.
CuPy is an open source project
developed by a Japanese company.
It provides NumPy compatible
ND-array on CUDA.
So, you can utilize all your GPU powers.
And also it is compatible with existing
CUDA kernel, meaning that you don't have
to waste your existing file, you just
need to import it
and then CUDA will run it for you.
It also provides many NumPy
equivalent functions.
So you don't have
to change your code a lot
and minimize the code refactoring effect.
But still, please remember CuPy
and NumPy has some difference.
Please check on CuPy's website
to find the details of difference
between CuPy and NumPy.
And one last thing, moving the data
between CPU and GPU is very expensive.
Please use it wisely. Otherwise, it
might not improve your performance,
but drag your performance a lot.
So, how do we implement
logsum exponential in CuPy?
It's quite easy, all you have
to do is import CuPy as CP
and then use the function
underlined here, cp.array to convert the
existing NumPy array to CuPy array,
and then CuPy does the metric for you.
And here's the final result,
as you can see our CuPy version,
the running time of our CuPy
version is just 1.6 seconds.
So, it's from like 6.5 seconds to 1.6
seconds. It's pretty amazing, right?
Now let's move on to the
next solution, Numba.
Numba is a very popular open source
project
that can boost your NumPy
and Python performance.
It is also backed
by many large companies and organizations.
The approach Numba uses
is called Just-In-Time technology.
Basically, it’s just translates a
subset of Python and NumPy code into
low-level machine code and runs faster.
It also utilizes both
CPU and GPU power.
One of the best things Numba has
is that it supports OpenMP, which means
that you can improve your market
ready program much, much faster.
The highlight of Numba is that it
provides near zero code modification.
All you have to do is to put a decorator,
@jit before the function you want to do
you want it to speed up
and Numba will take care of it.
And currently Numba only works
best with the functions not classes.
So, if you want to accelerate your
classes please do not use Numba.
Otherwise, you might
have a lot of issues with that.
And Numba also has a very large user
community, which means that if you have
any problems, you can find
the answer on the stack overflow.
When talking about Numba, there
are two modes you need to know.
The first one is nopython mode.
So in this mode Numba allows you
to get rid of Python’s GIL
so you can get
the most performance from it.
But not every function
is supported in nopython mode.
So sometimes you have to
switch back to the object mode.
In order to know which function is
supporting which mode,
you have to look up
the document in Numba’s website.
Luckily, the document itself is
very thorough, you shouldn't have
any problem to find out
which one works in which mode.
Finally, if you want to use OpenMP,
you must use it with the no JIT mode.
So basically, you only can
use it in the nopython mode.
And with that, here's
the sample code of the
OpenMP code, as you can see,
all I have to do is just
change the prange to prange,
and then Numba will recognize this
and then try to parallelize my code.
So, there's just one character change
and then I can get the most
performance out of Numba.
Now let's see how to implement
logsum exponential by Numba.
Here's the example I wrote.
As you can remember, when
you're looking at the code,
it's basically almost the same as
the one I implemented in NumPy.
Yes, that's correct, they
are exactly the same.
The only difference between
this one and the previous one
is that there are two
different decorators I put.
So, the first one is @jit and the
second one is @njit and
everything else is almost the
same, and here's the result.
As you can see, when using
the nopython mode with Numba,
the performance I get is about six seconds
but when switching back to the JIT mode,
it’s about 6.7 seconds.
I think it's about 0.2 second
slower than the original SciPy functions.
So, here's the very big difference.
If your function cannot
accelerate by Numba, sometimes
it will give you a worse result.
So be careful with that.
Now let's move on to the
last solution, Pythran.
Pythran is a relativity new open source
project written by a French developer.
It's under very active development as
it has a very fast-growing community.
Unlike Numba, which uses
just-in-time technology, Pythran uses
ahead-of-time compiling approach.
Basically, it means that it will
translate a part of your Python and NumPy
code into C++ and then utilize modern
compiler to compile and optimize your code
into a very efficient low-level
machine code, and it runs faster.
It also supports a subset of
Python and NumPy functions
and works on Python 2.7
and Python 3.6 to 3.8.
Just like Numba, all you have to do
is put a very special decorator
before the function you want to boost
and Pythran will take
the rest work for you.
It also supports OpenMP,
so you can utilize the full power
of a market-rated in your code.
So, how do we implement
logsum exponential in Pythran?
To use Pythran, normally
you need two steps.
First, you just write a Python code
as usual, so here is my sample code.
The only thing you have to do is put
a very special decorator over here
is #pythran export and then
your function now, and then
the data type of the input data.
And that's pretty much everything
you have to do,
and then the rest
is just like the one in NumPy.
After you finish editing the
file, all you have to do is compile.
You can use this very, very
long  code over here.
Or you can take an easier one. You
just use Pythran and then-- which part?
Over here, Pythran
and then your file name
and you will use all the default
argument to compile your code.
So, once you finish your code
and compile your code without any
compiling error roll, then
the second step is to import
the compiled module to the file.
So, you just create another file
and then import, just compile the
module over here, so here's the example.
And then all you have to do is just code
a function like you used to do in Python
so here is the code.
And the code will successful executed.
Here is the result of the Pythran.
As you can see, the result is much, much
faster than the NumPy’s nopython mode.
Sorry, it’s Numba’s nopython mode.
It only took 5.45 seconds to finish, it's
about one and half seconds faster than
Numba’s nopython mode.
So, if you want to get the full power
of your CPU,
please consider to use
Pythran to get the ultimate performance.
So, that’s it, I just introduced three
different approaches to improve your
Python and NumPy’s code performance.
So, right now, you might want to ask,
which is better?
Before we compare, I have to
tell you all the benchmark I ran
in the previous line is on a bare metal
machine with the following specifications.
The CPU I use is an Intel Xeon CPU.
And it comes with 256GB of RAM.
It also has a GeForce GTX 1080 Ti GPU.
The Python version I used is 3.6.9 on
Ubuntu and all the other libraries
and version information you
can find in this slide.
In this slide, I just put all previous
benchmark results into the same bar chart.
So, you can compare
the results by yourself.
The answer itself is quite clear.
If you have single or multiple
GPU, CuPy will be your best choice
because when you see the original function
in SciPy took about 6.7 seconds to finish.
CuPy only needed 1.6 seconds.
So, that's about five times
faster. It's just a no-brainer.
However, if you don't have any GPU,
don't worry.
You still have the other options.
So, as I mentioned before,
original SciPy function took 6.7.
In this scenario, I will
suggest you to try Numba first.
Because Numba supports more
NumPy solutions than Pythran.
So, after you give your Numba a try,
you will find that in no JIT mode,
Numba can successfully compile an SQ, and
it will give you about 0.7 seconds faster
and from now on you can
give the Pythran another try.
So if the same function also
is supported in Pythran,
then it can give you
extra performance boost.
In my case, Pythran can
work in my benchmark code.
So, the total execution time
of Pythran is 5.4 seconds.
So, by comparing to
the original SciPy's version,
it's about 20% or 25% faster
than original solution.
That’s not bad for just change a few lines
of code and get extra 20% of performance
I can call  you it a day.
At the end, I would like to show
you my own decision tree to CuPy,
Numba and Pythran.
Here is my decision tree. So,
the first question starting with,
do you have GPU?
If you do have GPU then the
follow up question will be,
do you need to use CUDA kernel or do you
need to implement your own CUDA kernel?
If the answer is still yes, then I will
strongly recommend you to use CuPy.
If the answer is no, then
the follow up question will be,
do you also have
the CPU computation task with your GPU?
If the answer is yes, then
Numba will be a better choice.
Otherwise, please stay with CuPy.
If you don't have any GPU,
you still have options, right?
So, the question itself will
be very, very easy.
Do you like to deal with compiler?
So, if the answer is no, then I
would suggest that you use Numba.
So, it will only give you
very minimal compiling errors.
And if you are a geek and you like
to deal with the compiler, compiling flags
and all the compiling error logs, and
then of course Pythran can give you
the most of these.
And also, if you choose Pythran as in
the example I demo in a previous page
and also in my real work,
Pythran can almost always give me
the most CPU power, all of it.
So, I will suggest that if you
want to achieve the best performance
with CPU, Pythran
will be your best choice.
Finally, at the end of this, I would
like to provide three takeaways for you.
First, if you have GPU please try CuPy
first. It's really easy to use CuPy.
Just import CuPy as CP, and then
code NumPy’s functions with CuPy.
But there's one thing
you have to remember,
please remember to convert
NumPy’s array to CuPy’s array,
so CuPy can help you to move the data from
physical memory to graphic card memory.
Second, if you only have
GPU, that's totally fine
because you still have options.
In this case, I will suggest
you to use Numba first,
because Numba supports more
NumPy functions than Pythran
and I would strongly recommend
you to use Numba in its nopython mode.
If your code runs smoothly
with Numba in nopython mode,
then I would suggest that you try
Pythran to get more performance.
In my company's case, we can get the
most CPU power with Pythran every time.
So, it's very worth to give it a try.
Finally, each solution support
different numbers of NumPy functions.
Luckily, each solution has a very
well written and maintained website.
So you can easily find the support
functions this on each solutions website.
So just give it a look.
Also, it's fairly easy to find out which
function doesn't work
because normally your program will just die
if the function is not supported
by the proposed solution.
And also, if A doesn’t work, B might
work.
So, if for example, if Pythran doesn't work,
you can always give Numba a try.
And in reality, especially during my work,
I always try to use a mixture
of these three proposed methods.
So, sometimes I will use Numba
with Pythran or CuPy with Pythran.
So, it's all up to you. I will suggest
that you to give a mixture solution a try.
So, that's pretty much all my talk.
Thank you. And I hope you stay
safe during the COVID-19 pandemic.