Hello Everyone.
My name is Gajendra Deshpande.
and today I will be presenting a talk on
Python and FOSS in Education
for Generation Z.
So, FOSS is nothing but
Free and Open-Source Software.
So these are the contents which we are going to
discuss today
The Generation Z.
So that means who are the
students who belongs to Generation Z?
Then BYOD. So, what do we mean by BYOD
and how it is important in education?
What are its advantages and disadvantages?
Then we're going to discuss a few
tools, such as QPython, Blockly, VisuPy,
then TextBook Companion Project
and Flowgorithm,
then how we can build new
programming language support.
it is the example, for Julia language and how
we can create it using Python template.
Then finally, future goals.
So, Generation Z. So, these are the people
who are born between 1995 and 2010.
So, these are the true digital natives.
That is, from their earliest youth
they have been exposed to the internet,
social networks and mobile systems.
That means they are all
gadget-oriented people.
So, you see uh--
they use a lot of gadgets like mobile
phones or even earphones, et cetera.
So, these are very tech savvy people,
and they believe in hands on learning.
So, and if you consider the teachers now,
they are not belong to-- they
don't belong to Generation Z.
They belong to the previous generations,
that is, Generation Y and Generation X.
Then BYOD stands for
Bring Your Own Device.
So, with BYOD you are creating
1:1 classroom.
Students bring and use
their own devices,
their own choice of
technological devices in the classroom.
So, BYOD has got many
advantages and disadvantages.
The benefits of BYOD are that
your students know the device,
because after all it is
their device so they know
clearly how to use that device.
So, you do not have to worry
about the device’s configurations.
So, it shows that technology
has many possibilities
and cutting-edge devices
are possible because generally,
whenever students buy any gadgets,
they buy the recent one
and it is cost-effective from
the side of an institution.
So, institution does not have to invest
much in procuring the advanced devices.
Then, learning outside
the school hours is possible.
Then respect for the device
since it is their device,
they use the device very carefully.
So otherwise, if it’s the institute’s
device or if it's another’s device,
then they may not use it with care.
Then it also helps in building
the organized student community.
Then the disadvantages of BYOD
that is, bring your own devices, are that
there are students without devices.
Because of their financial
conditions, they may not be able to buy
the devices,
even maybe a simple phone.
Then, the different devices,
we don't have control here.
Each student has got his own,
or her own device preferences,
their own configurations.
So, it may create problems sometimes
whenever they want to connect to
a classroom, or to a teacher’s
system in a classroom
because some may have Android-
based mobile phone,
some may have iOS-based
mobile phones, and so on.
Then, it also creates a distraction
because students may
also use it for other purposes.
Maybe they may use the device for chatting
apart from learning inside the classroom.
Then, it results into a
not-responsible student.
Now many countries have got BYOD policy.
That means, if you see the example here
Austria, USA and many countries in Europe,
like Estonia, Finland, Norway, Portugal,
Switzerland, United Kingdom, Australia.
So, they have the BYOD policies.
They encourage BYOD in the classroom.
Even in India,
the ICT is encouraging the use of, bring
your own devices concept in the classroom.
Now, as we know that because of BYOD,
the students will be able to use-- are
able to bring their own device and use it.
So, most of the times when we say,
bring your own device,
actually it is the laptop, but many people
or many students here, what we have
observed is they don't get their laptops
because of various reasons. Some
may not have purchased it or some,
they don't want to bring it.
So for them, there is a solution that most
of the people they have the smart phones.
So, you can use the smart phone
for teaching-learning process.
So, what we can do now is if we
are teaching a class using Python,
or if you are teaching a Python course
in the classroom,
then there is a very nice
mobile application called QPython.
So, it basically runs only
on Android now. Okay.
So, QPython is a script engine which
runs Python programs on Android devices.
It also can help developers
develop Android applications.
So, you can also develop
here web applications.
It has also got the support
of Jupyter Notebooks.
Then the advantages are that you
can easily develop the applications.
So, QPython includes
a complete development kit,
which helps you to develop
programs with the mobile.
And it is very powerful
because you can extend it as you want.
Then it has got great support.
So, commercial support can support
your development with QPython API or
Embed QPython SDK,
that is Software Development Kit.
So, it can save you a lot of time.
Yeah. So, to download QPython,
you have to visit www.qpython.com.
It comes with two versions. One is
qpython and second one is qpython3.
So, whatever the screen you're
seeing here, a screenshot.
So, it's the welcome screen
of QPython software.
So, you can see here two more screenshots
like QPython also supports Terminal
and it also supports the Jupyter Notebook.
It can execute Python programs on
Terminal and Notebook on Android programs.
So, let us see the small demo here.
So, what I have done here is I have
installed QPython on my mobile phone
and I have connected to my mobile
phone’s screen on laptop using TeamViewer.
So, there is a option now, QPython OL.
So, you can click on that.
So, you can see here
we have got the same
screen, which we had seen.
Now the important ones are here-- three
options; Terminal, Editor and Explorer.
If I click on Terminal, so you can see
here it is showing me the Terminal window.
Here I can directly start
typing the Python code.
Let's say, I'll say 10+20
and when I press enter,
we can see here it is
showing me the result, 30.
Let me also try to
print some message here.
Print (“Hello Qpython”).
Okay. So, you can see here
it has printed the message.
Now, let me come out of this
by typing exit.
Yeah. So again, I'm back on my screen.
Now, there is also an option called Editor.
So, you can type your entire program--
entire Python program here,
and you can save it and also run it.
So, I'll write,
(Hello PyCon Korea”).
Okay. So, this is what I have typed.
Now you can see here,
there's a run button. Okay.
When you click on run button, it says,
Warning: Do you want
to save the changes first?
So, you can say Yes to save the file.
Now you have to specify
the message file name here.
So, let's say, hello1.py, and save it.
So, you can see that message at the top
that it's saved and you can also note
the changes from untitled to hello1.py.
Now again, let's click on run.
There is some error here.
That's-- that's fine.
So, let's go back
and modify--
modify the program-- yeah.
So, after that you can save it.
Now let's run it.
Yeah. So, you can see here
that it is showing the message
that program has run successfully.
So, then there is also a
third option called Explorer.
So, come to Explorer here then you can see
there is an option called Notebooks.
So, there are some
Jupyter Notebooks here.
So, let's click on Welcome.ipynb file.
Note there that if you want to open
a Jupyter Notebook and work with it,
the option has to be enabled.
Then only you will be able
to start the Jupyter Notebook.
Let's see what happens here.
Yeah. So, it says-- please
enable QPyNotebook in the setting.
Let’s say, OK.
But it was already enabled here,
so not a problem.
Yeah, so I'm able to open it here.
So you can see here that
there are already some code written.
So, to run any code block just click
on that and run this option, next option
and again run next option.
Right. So, you can see it
whenever you are clicking on run.
So, it is now running the program.
Right.
Okay. So, it has printed
a message, Hello 10.
So, just a small message
has appeared on the screen.
So, this Qpython is very, very useful tool
to be used in the classroom.
So, now again, let's move
back to our presentation here.
So, this was about QPython.
The next tool is Google Blockly.
So, Blockly is a library
created by Google.
It's basically created using JavaScript.
It supports many languages.
So, it's a library for building
visual programming editors.
Blockly is a library that adds visual code
editor to web and mobile applications.
The Blockly editor uses
interlocking graphical blocks
to represent code concepts like variables,
logical expressions, loops, and more.
So, it allows users to apply
programming principles
without having to worry about syntax
or the intimidation of blinking
cursor on the command line.
So basically, if you have played zigsaw
puzzle game, so it looks exactly like that.
So, you have different code blocks
you need to drag and drop
appropriate code block
and make the appropriate setting there.
So, together it creates a
code block and you can run it.
So, you need not have to worry about
the syntax of the programming language.
So, from the user's perspective, Blockly
is an intuitive visual way to build code.
From a developer’s perspective, Blockly is
a ready-made user interface for creating a
visual language that emits
syntactically correct user-generated code.
Then next, Blockly can export blocks to
many programming languages, including
JavaScript, Python, PHP, Lua,
and Dart. It also supports Arduino.
Now, if you want to build a
different language support,
the entire Blockly source code
is available. It's open source.
You can refer to their documentation,
and you can generate the support
for your own language.
Now Blockly is one of the growing
number of visual programming environments.
Deciding which one to use in
your application is an important step.
So, here are a few Blockly’s biggest
strengths to help you make the decision.
So, first one is the exportable code.
Users can extract their block-based
programs to common programming languages
and smoothly transition
to text-based programming.
The next one is the open source.
Everything about Blockly is open.
You can fork it, hack it and use it in
your own sites and Android applications.
Then, extensible. Tweak Blockly to
fit your needs by adding custom blocks
for your API, or removing
unneeded blocks and functionality.
Then, it is highly capable.
Blockly is not a toy. You can
implement complex programming tasks
like calculating standard
deviation in a single block.
It is truly international.
That is Blockly has translated
to 40 plus languages,
including right-to-left
versions for Arabic and Hebrew.
Okay. So, whatever you are
seeing on this screen now is the
basic user interface of Blockly.
And you can see here that
this is a very simple code
which prints Hello World
message for up to three times,
and up to four times.
Basically, here--
you can see that on the left
side you have the Blockly code
and on the right hand side it is the--
generated code in Python language.
Let's see how it works.
Let’s see the demo again.
So yeah-- so you can visit this
site, developers.google.com/blockly.
So, you can see that this is the
basic code which is written and loaded.
So, if you want, you can modify it.
So, you can see here that these
are the languages supported;
JavaScript, Python, PHP, Lua
and Dart. Let us select Python here.
Now see here when we select Python,
the code has been now converted
to Python language.
Now let’s click on run button.
Now it says, Hello World, first time,
second time, third time, fourth time.
Okay, so four times Hello World
has been printed.
So, these are the different blocks.
So, you can see here
there are different blocks.
You just need to drag and drop it here.
Right. When you drag and drop it here,
it will generate the
corresponding code automatically.
So, you can see here.
So, it has generated the code.
It is generating the code.
So, whenever you want, you
can just go on putting the block.
So, just for demonstration
purposes, I'll write some value here,
but I will not execute these code blocks.
So, this is just for demonstration.
Okay. So, likewise, you have got several
other options for functions and etc.
Right. Even for mathematical operations--
there are functionalities.
So, square root of nine,
and I just drag and drop it here
so it generates the code for it.
So, it's very simple to use
and it's a great tool
and you can see here there are a lot
of things which are built using Blockly.
So, you can do a lot of great things.
So, let's move back to presentation again.
Yeah. So, next tool is the VisuPy.
This is the code visualization tool.
Actually, this was one of the
projects in CERN’s Webfest 2020.
So, some team has created it.
I don't have the exact details,
but if you go to the following link,
that is, webfest.cern/projects,
you will get the link
and there is also a video on it.
So, you can watch the video
to understand how it works.
So, basically, what you can
see here is it is just the opposite
of whatever you have seen earlier.
So, what your Blockly does is it generates
this source code from the blocks.
Okay, you are dragging and
dropping the blocks, and once it is done,
you are generating the source code.
But here you have the opposite
way. You have the source code here,
and you want to understand
the working of the source code
and flow of the source code.
So, in this case from source code, you
are generating the visualization. Okay.
Then next, this is also a great
project related to Python.
So, it is known as Python Textbook
Companion project by FOSSEE
that is in IIT Bombay, India.
So the Textbook Companion activity aims to
create a repository of reference material
for Python by coding solved examples of
standard engineering textbooks using Python.
So, this activity intends to
make individuals learn Python
through a practical approach,
provide a huge database of companions
as a learning resource
to make it easy for resources-- to
make it easy for users of such textbooks
to start using Python, to improve the
documentation available for Python.
So, here--
it was an interesting project.
So, what to do is, there are some
textbooks so you need to select a textbook
and from the textbook, you need to pick
the examples
and you have to write the code
in Python language.
So, in this way, they created a
huge database of Python programs,
which can be used in teaching
that particular subject
but with Python examples.
So, it was, again, a
very interesting concept.
Right now, they are not accepting
any proposals, but in the past
many have participated here and the
advantage is that the selected fellows
will be paid by FOSSEE project
and they have been paid in the past.
So, to get more details you can visit this
Website: https:tbc-python.fossee.in
So this is the user interface,
so if you visit
this website you will get all the
details like who can contribute,
how to contribute, what are
the guidelines for coding?
Everything is mentioned here
on this site.
The next interesting
tool is the Flowgorithm.
So Flowgorithm is a free
beginner's programming tool
that is based on simple
graphical flow charts.
So, it looks almost similar
to Google Blockly,
but it has a different concept
because it deals with the flow charts.
So typically, when a student
first learns a program,
they often use one of the
text-based programming languages.
Depending on the language, this can
either be easy or frustratingly difficult.
Many languages require you
to write lines of confusing code
just to display the text: Hello World.
By using flow charts, you can concentrate
on programming concepts rather than
all the nuances of
a difficult programming language.
So, you can also run your
program directly in the Flowgorithm.
So, once you understand
the program logic it is easy
for you to learn one
of the major languages.
So, Flowgorithm can interactively
convert your flowchart
to over 18 programming languages.
So, it includes C#, C++, Java,
JavaScript, Lua, Perl, also Python,
then Ruby, Swift,
Visual Basic .NET and so on.
So, the greatest advantage
of Flowgorithm, what I see here is--
so, we see that many students’
native language is not English.
They come from rural backgrounds.
They don't have access to
the English medium
education in their early education.
So it becomes difficult for them to catch
up with English medium instructions.
So, in that case, we can use
tools like Flowgorithm or Blockly
where they can just
concentrate on building the logic
instead of the syntax and semantics
of the programming language.
So, that's a great way of teaching
programming for beginners
whose native language is not English.
So, Flowgorithm has
some features-- that is, it--
there is easy to understand output,
graphical variable watch window.
Then it can interactively
generate a real code,
that is 18+ languages
including Python is supported.
It also supports safe recursion.
It supports loops, arrays,
and flexible expressions.
Then it also supports multilingual
support, including Korean.
So, user interface you can
have in your own language,
you can draw a flowchart in your own
language.
That's the advantage here.
If you don't find the language for--
If you don't find the support for
your language then you can write
to the creator of Flowgorithm--
to Devin Cook.
So, he will provide you the file
and you can translate and send him.
so he will integrate it
into Flowgorithm software.
So, we know that flowchart
means there are some symbols.
So, these are the symbols
which are supported here.
So, you have support for
comments and breakpoints.
Then you also have input/output symbols.
Then you have variables
symbol, then control flow statement,
function calls, looping statements.
So, all the basic flowchart
symbols are supported.
Now, so you can see here, this is
a simple program which is created.
So what it does is it just
controls the sum of your numbers.
So, on the left side, you can see that--
see here, that there's a flow chart
and on the right-hand side, it
generates the source code in Python.
Then
on the right bottom corner, you
can see the output of the program.
So, let's see the demo again
for Flowgorithm.
So, when you start Flowgorithm
you will get this window here.
Let me--
if you want to change the language
so you can see here.
So, it supports so many
languages, including Korean.
Then also, there is
so let's change the view layout windows.
So, I would like to have flowchart code
as well as output in the same window.
So, that's why I have chosen this.
So, let me--
open some program here.
Okay.
Okay, that's fine. So, let's
print a Hello message program.
So, let's select Hello, output
symbol, then just double-click on it.
Then in our code just write
message here, Hello Flowgorithm,
and say OK.
So, you can see here, it has
generated the code in Python.
So similarly, if you click here,
you can see here that it
supports so many languages, right?
Now with a change of the
source code, now let’s run it.
And you can see here at the bottom
it has displayed the output. Okay?
So, this is about the Flowgorithm tool.
So, you can visit
Flowgorithm website here.
That is, flowgorithm.org to
get to know about more details.
Now--
let's go to the next concept,
how we can support or how we
can build support for a new language--
for a new language for
Flowgorithm using templates.
So, if you visit this URL,
that is the documentation URL,
so some templates are mentioned here.
Lua, Java, Pascal and Python
templates are mentioned.
Let’s download the Python template. I
already downloaded the Python template.
So, it’s in TXT file.
So, you can just go on mentioning--
go on making the changes here.
So, I wanted to create the
support for Julia language.
So, instead of Python I’ll write Julia.
I write extension as .jl.
I will list here Julia’s keywords.
Then similarly, I will also
make appropriate changes here,
appropriate changes at appropriate places.
Let's say, for example,
the expressions syntaxes will be changed.
Then, yeah. So, Julia doesn't
support some operators here.
So, I need to make
appropriate changes here.
Then some intrinsic functions.
So, whatever functions my language
supports that I have to mention here.
So, if something is not supported,
just remove it.
Okay. So similarly, you can see these are
the syntax of Python programming language.
So I don't want it here. So just
replace the syntax of your own language.
So, in my case, I will
replace it with Julia.
So, I have already done it.
It's available on my GitHub repository,
Okay. So, once it is done you
need to save it with an extension .fpgt
So, that is Flowgorithm template file.
And what you should be doing here
when you generate the
source code is that-- yeah,
so instead of Python here, now you need
to select the appropriate template file.
So open template file, and there's the
Julia template file and then I say open.
So, you can see here that it…
Okay, fine. I think there is some
problem, fine.
But it selects the code.
Appropriate code will be generated. So--
let’s to go back to our presentation again.
So, the advantage
is that it's easy to use,
drag and drop and corresponding
code generation is possible.
It is very beginner-friendly and a
great tool to learn problem solving.
So, code generation is limited.
For example, two or more
dimensional arrays are not supported.
So, language-specific features
are not supported many times.
Presently no support for Indic languages.
So, we need to develop
support for Indic languages,
especially with respect
to the user interface
so that it can reach to the villages
and it can reach to the students
of village at their early age
so that they can be introduced.
They can put in that at early age.
Yeah. So, this we have seen.
Then the future goals is that
add Indic language support for Flowgorithm
and customize Blockly for more languages.
Then, more code visualization
tools can be developed.
Then, more gamified tools are required
to enhance learning and to create a better
experience of learning for students.
Thank you, everyone
for your patience listening--
patient listening and providing me
an opportunity to speak at PyCon Korea.
Thank you.
Thank you everyone.