Hello, good time of the day.
Welcome to my talk.
Today, I'm going to be talking about
Building Petabyte Scale Machine
Learning Models Using Python,
specifically Tensorflow and Pytorch.
Before we get started
just a quick introduction.
My name is Vaibhav Srivastav.
You can call me VB.
I have spoken at PyCon
Korea by before as well -
in fact, last year I gave a
workshop as well as a talk.
Throughout this talk duration,
if you have any questions
and whenever you're watching the talk,
feel free to tweet out to me @reach_vb.
If you want to find my blog, or
if you want to find my email ID,
you can go to vaibhav.blog.
You would find the information
on the bottom left
about my Twitter handle
as well as my website.
Now, without further ado
let's get started.
Now before we get started, I
want to try something new here, right?
So, before we begin the actual talk,
I want to spend a minute
and I want to convince you why distributed
machine learning is something
that you should be passionate about,
and something that you
should be excited about.
For that, what we did was
we ran a couple of benchmarks
on Tensorflow and Pytorch,
both on CPU as well as a couple of
GPUs for an image classification task.
Now what we did for this task was
we took the CIFAR-10 dataset.
This data set, mind, has
roughly about 10 classes,
some 60,000-odd images,
and what we did was we--
we provisioned an n1-standard-4 instance
on Google Cloud Platform.
And you can find
the hardware details down below.
We also provisioned a couple of GPUs
which were NVIDIA Tesla T4.
And the intention was that
we run multiple experiments
by changing the number of work
codes, by changing the number of GPUs,
changing the number of CPUs,
and then measuring how much
of a time difference or how
much of a speedup difference
does the code actually get?
All right, let's go to the results.
Now, after running
multiple such experiments,
we found that both for Tensorflow
as well as for Pytorch,
the overall speedup when
you're training the model
it increases manifold times as you
increase the number of workers.
Now specifically in the case of both
in the case of Tensorflow, as well as
in the case of Pytorch GPU, on your left
you would see that the overall speedup
relative to one worker, meaning how
much time would you spend while you're
running your entire machine learning
modeling exercise on your own laptop
or just on one worker.
If you compare that with running the
same exercise with multiple workers,
you would see that the overall speedup
is you know, manifold times more than
what it should be, right?
What it should be
when you only have one worker.
And you would see that the
overall speedup is pretty much the…
is pretty much the...
it follows the same trend across
CPU, as well as GPUs, right?
What that tells us is as
you increase the parallelism,
as you increase the distribution
in your overall cluster,
your overall time to train your machine
learning model decreases.
And you can also get the same inferences
from the graph on the right as well.
The graph on the right talks
specifically about two key--
about two key parameters, right?
The first one is the compute
that is-- how much of an--
how much of my overall clocks
are being put into training my module.
Second is communication. How much
of an IO overhead do I have
between my workers or between the dataset
and my overall training exercise.
And you would see clearly that as
we increase the number of workers
both the overall communication overhead
also decreases, as well as the--
the overall number of-- the overall
time taken to achieve 80% accuracy,
meaning, the overall time taken
for the model
to become 80% accurate on the dataset
also decreases.
So, this is a clear case for building
distributed machine learning pipelines.
If this looks a bit confusing to you
bear with me for a couple more minutes.
I'm just going to get into
demystifying this-- this entire stuff.
But I wanted to start off and then give
you like a real-life example of how much
easy does your life becomes when you build
a distributed machine learning pipeline
and when you train it—
when you train your models at scale.
They not only run faster, they
also execute your entire pipeline in a
much faster fashion, and reach the
benchmark accuracy in a more faster way.
Just a quick thing.
All of these benchmarks
were taken from MLBench.
MLBench is a joint
initiative with PWC, Google,
a couple other academic
institutes as well.
You can find the link to that
on the bottom right.
So, just click on that and
you'll be able to get both the code
as well as the benchmark results as well
and a detailed explanation of how those
jobs were run, and what actually
happened around those as well.
All right, now that you've got
a bit of feel of what
distributed machine learning can do,
let's go through
let's go through the
agenda real quick, right?
So, today we're going to be
covering like six key things.
First, we're going to be talking about why
do we need distributed machine learning.
We're going to get a broader intuition
of how distributed machine learning works.
What are different types of machine
learning, distributed machine learning?
Then we're going to be specifically
talking about out of core machine learning
which is a type of
distributed machine learning,
and then we spend a
bit of time talking about
how do we actually build these scalable
machine learning workflows?
And do some sort of discussion around
what sort of frameworks Tensorflow does,
Pytorch. What should you use
in order to be able to build
those scalable machine
learning workflows?
Last but not the least my favorite part,
we're going to be doing code walk-through.
We're going to be, you know, talking
by Python, we're going
to be talking Tensorflow
and we're going to be going
through both of these frameworks
and I've prepared some sweet Colab
notebooks for you that you can use
and leverage later on when you're
building your machine learning pipelines.
Then towards the end, we're going
to finish up with some sort of questions
and answers that you can
put on the comments or
you know, you can tweet out to me on
my tweet handle on the bottom left side.
Cool. Let's get started.
So, first of all, why do we need
distributed machine learning?
While we answer this entire
question, let's take a step back.
And let's look at how a typical
machine learning exercise look like.
In a typical machine learning exercise,
you would have some sort of data, right?
This data can be, images, can
be text, can be audio signals,
can be anything like that.
And you would have some
sort of a task to do with it.
You would have a task, like,
for example, classification
or you could have a task like regression
or forecasting,
something like that, right?
Let's take an example.
Say you have a box full of balls.
So, a simple classification
task in that would be that you
take all the balls of red color
and put them into another box.
You take all the balls of blue color
and put them into one different box.
That's basically classification, right?
So, you're classifying your data.
So, you have some data and you
have a task to perform with that. Simple.
Now, how do you actually train a machine
learning model to learn that task?
You would have some sort of an algorithm
which would be consuming this data
and would be churning
out your entire task.
Now for a very simple, you know,
classification example, let's
pick the balls example itself.
For that example, you will have some
sort of a model like logistic regression
or say a neural network or Naive Bayes,
some sort of an algorithm
like that …
to sort of take the data that you
have and classify that data for that.
And in case of regression, you would
have either say an ARIMA model
or say a linear regression
or random forest regression,
decision tree regression, all sorts
of things that are present right now.
Bottom line is for a given data and
for a given task, you would have a model
or some sort of an
algorithm solving for X, right?
And then you would have, like--
for this model to be able to
give you the best possible results, you
would have some sort of a loss criteria
or some sort of an optimization criteria.
Now, what this optimization
criteria effectively would be,
is that this loss criteria would tell you
at what point in your equation plane--
At what time, at what point in the
entire plane of your n-dimensional data
where exactly do you get a curve
or do you get like-- get a surface
that best describes
your entire data?
So, in a two dimensional
plane, that can be Y=MX+C.
So, how do you get that?
By finding the exact equation
of that line wherein the overall loss
from where your data
is, is the least.
So, you have some
sort of a loss function.
In like a regression scenario you would
have something like mean squared error
or, you know, R squared score, or
RMSE, something like that, right?
So, you have a loss function.
So again, you have the data, you
have a task, you have a model
and then you have your loss function.
Then like, you know, like what
function do you have to minimize, right?
You know what function
do you have to minimize.
Then you will have some sort of
an optimization procedure.
In a very simple neural network,
you would typically use something like
either gradient descent or stochastic
gradient descent wherein you're like--
you’re taking small, small steps
across the plain of your data
and you're trying to see what's
the value of your loss there.
If your loss is very low, then you say--
if your loss is lower than
the previous loss,
then you say that this is a
step in the right direction, right?
And you keep on traversing
through all the curves,
all the data points within
your datasets across n dimensions.
And that's how towards the end,
once your loss starts plateauing
to a particular point,
then you know that
this is the most optimal
plain or most optimal equation
for representing your data.
So again, you have the data, you
have the task, you have your model,
you have your loss
criteria and you have your--
optimization procedure, right?
So, far so good, a very simple neural net
or a very simple machine learning model,
which is performing a
task that you've given to it.
Now--
all the way up until here,
let me go back.
And now all the way up until
here, everything's good. Right?
You can read your data into pandas.
You can import some sort of a library
say, scikit-learn, you can import
say random forest or decision trees,
build your model, look at the overall
evaluation and you're good to go, right?
And you know this kind of setup
would work all right.
And effectively, right now, you won't see
a need for distributed machine learning.
So, then why do we actually
need machine learning?
Why do we actually
need distributed machine learning?
We need it specifically in cases
where you have massive data scale
or you have massive model scale.
And you know, in the third case,
maybe you just want efficient computation
of your algorithms.
Maybe you have
a very complex optimization strategy
and you know it takes a lot
of time and you want to divide that across
a couple of machines
to be able to reduce that.
So let's spend a minute
on this slide, right?
So, what does massive data scale mean?
So, one of the first things is that
when we talk about data scale,
it is very relative.
What I mean by that is, for
a computer or for a laptop
with 16GB of RAM, you
know, 32GB of data is something
which is big data, right?
Which is massive data for a
laptop with 16GB of RAM.
Whereas for a Raspberry Pi with just 1GB of RAM or with just 2GB of RAM,
even like 4GB of data would be very huge.
So, your massive data scale depends upon
what kind of a machine or what kind of
what kind of cluster are you
running your analytics pipeline
or your machine learning pipeline on.
Similarly, model scale
can also have multiple meanings.
So, a model can be big.
Say for example, a neural network can
be, say 500MB in size or say --
say 1000MB in size.
Actually, know what, let me go back, sorry.
So, when we talk about
massive model scales,
effectively, what we mean
by a massive model scale is
the overall architecture
of your model itself, right?
So, for example, when we talk about
say Naïve Bayes or say a random forest
or decision trees, those are
actually quite small models, right?
Why? Because those are effectively
a bunch of mathematical equations
and their corresponding values in
an overall rated circuit. Right?
Rated graph.
Whereas when you talk about, say
something which is as complex as,
say for example neural
collaborative filtering,
or say, convolutional neural
networks, or recurrent neural networks,
then those models would have your overall
embedding of the data itself, as well as
the weights for individual
nodes on the architecture itself,
which would sometimes correspond
to massive data sizes.
Sorry, model sizes.
Those model sizes could be 1GB,
could be 10GB
or in case of say-- you know some
models that you see right now like GPT-3,
those could be like of the order
of you know, couple-- you know,
of the order of tens or
twenties of gigabytes as well,
something that does not
even fit in your RAM as well.
So, in those scenarios as well, you
will need distributed machine learning
so that you can infer out
of that model itself, right?
Then comes the third one, which is
efficient computation of your algorithm,
which is say, for example, if
you're running across massive data
and you have a very large architecture,
then you will need a mechanism to be able
to execute your algorithms
in the fastest possible manner, right?
In the most efficient manner--
wherein you are utilizing maximum
of your existing resources without
overwhelming them or without creating
a bottleneck in between two processes.
And that's where efficient computation
of algorithms comes into place.
This can be something as simple as, if
we take our case of balls again, right?
So, say, for example,
you have one box of balls,
and you want to segregate red
and blue into two different boxes,
then one scenario can be that you are the
only one who is segregating those balls.
Whereas in a second scenario,
you can ask a friend of yours.
And you can say,
“Hey man, can you help me?
Can you take half of these balls
and can you separately segregate them
into red and blue?”
Now, what you've effectively done is
you've reduced the overall workload
on yourself,
and you've added another person
to help you out with
the task of segregation.
And that's actually a
Gold mine, right?
Why, because one
you've reduced the load on you,
which means that you will be able to
complete your task in roughly X by 2 times
and at the same time, the other
person is also doing the other half of it.
So, what that means is
you've effectively halved
the time that you were
previously taking, right?
And that gives you speed up.
That's the most simplest case
of distributing a task.
So, that's distributed
machine learning 101 for you.
Moving ahead.
If we go like more detailed
If we go into more details
about how this actually works
is by-- like the example
that we just spoke about.
That's something which
is called Out-of-Core ML.
What Out-of-Core ML does is,
it is basically an algorithm which
uses external storage.
And, you know,
essentially what it would do is
it would train your model
on small chunks of data.
So, let's take a different example now.
Say, for example, you're building a
forecasting model for your stock prices.
Say you want to model the
stock prices of Tesla, right?
Now, you would take past the
couple years of Tesla prices.
Say at a [inaudible], right?
That gives you
like very large data frame, right?
That now you have to train an
overall forecasting model on.
So, what you do is
you divide the overall
dataset into multiple chunks.
You take one year of data first
and you train your model on that.
You persist the weights of that, and
then for the second year of data,
you start training from those
weights and you train on those weights.
Then you repeat this process
for the third year of data, for the
fourth year of the data, for the fifth
year of the data and so on and so forth.
What is helps you do is it does not
overwhelm your overall architecture.
And it would effectively
help you run--
help you run or or help you train models
on very large data sets as well.
And you can easily parallelize
these tasks as well, right?
Because more often than not
these can be independent tasks.
So, you can independently train 12
different models on 12 years of data,
and then you can-- you know,
combine their weights
and come up with some sort of
averaged model on top of that as well.
So that's what Out-of-Core ML is,
which means that effectively like
instead of loading the entire data dataset
into your RAM in one go, you only
load some bit of data first,
and then you divide and conquer.
I hope that gives you good enough
details on what Out-of-Core ML is,
because that's what we're going
to build on in the slides to come.
Now, let's go back to
our drawing board.
We spoke about having a dataset,
having a task, you know,
having a model and then our last
function, and then having some sort
of optimization function
on top of it, right?
Now, let's take that
example and let's add the--
let's add the mix of
distributed ML on that.
So, if we were to distribute
the overall task as we said before
into two different nodes,
how would we do that?
You would, first of all,
at the ground level--
You would partition your
data into two sets.
You would have a data set partition one,
and you would have a
data set partition two, right?
Your task remains the same.
If it's classification, it's the same.
If it's regression, it remains the
same, for both the partitions.
What changes is that, except like
previously you were running that task
or say classification
on the entire set of data,
now you run it on a smaller set--
smaller partition of data.
Your model remains the same again.
So, if you were using a
convolution neural net before,
again, you would use the same CNN, same
architecture across both the partitions.
Your loss function updates.
And this is kind of obvious.
Why, because your loss function earlier
was giving you the value of your loss for
just for the entire dataset.
But now, you're training
your entire model on a partition.
So now you need to have a loss that
is computed on that partition itself,
not on the entire dataset.
So, loss function gets updated.
Also, your overall optimization strategy
would also be updated.
Why, because now you need to-- like,
even though you're training
your models into two silos--
But you still need to optimize
it to get one global minimum.
Right? One global minimum.
And the simplest way of
doing that can be that you
have an F1 of X or like whatever
optimization value that you get,
you add for both the partitions.
And how this will be achieved is
through having some sort of communication
and complexity and--
basically having like asynchronous
communication happening
between the two datasets.
It says that, “Hey, I just finished say
X data points, and these are my weights.
So, why don't you look at this?”
And say that,
“You know, Hey, I just finished this,
and these are my weights,”
and so on and so forth.
So communication keeps
on happening between the two.
between the two.
And that’s the simplest way of building
a distributed machine learning pipeline.
Right? If I was to scale this up, I
can have N number of data partitions
working on N number
of working nodes, right?
Running effectively the same code except
running it on small, small chunks of data.
And then I aggregate their overall losses
to get the best possible manner.
So again, this does the same thing,
right? It reduces the overall time for
running your machine learning model.
Not only that, it also helps you
get from your data all the weight
and insights as soon as possible.
Now, enough theoretical stuff, right?
If we were to do this in
action, how we do this?
In real life, you could do it in two ways
without going into too much details.
The first one would be if-- say
you're familiar with scikit-learn,
the first method would be to use
something known as partial_fit, right?
You can do like a model
toward partial_fit.
What partial_fit does, is it effectively
helps you build incremental models.
So, it isn't parallelizing your task
but what it's doing is it's giving
you the capability to train a model
on larger datasets, larger
than your RAM datasets--
on your laptop or on your virtual
machine, whatever it may be.
And this is particularly useful if you're
already familiar with how Dask-ML works
or how scikit-learn works and
so on and so this would follow
the same kind of methodology.
In fact, scikit-learn has a couple
of models which support partial_fit.
And again, what this would do is it
would take small chunks of your data
and sequentially train your model on
those small chunks, and then aggregate
the overall weights
and aggregate the overall equations,
your final equation
on the basis of that.
For example, is a
stochastic gradient descent,
regressor stochastic gradient
descent classifier in scikit-learn,
which supports partial_fit as well.
So, you can use that and effectively
you can train a machine learning model
on a dataset of size 32 GB
with just a RAM of 8 GB as well,
because it will take only say
4GB chunk in one go,
process them, and then take the
next 4GB chunk,
take the next 4GB chunk and so on.
So, this will never give you
out of memory error.
The second way, which is something
which I personally recommend as well
if you're starting off from scratch is
to do a graph-based model training.
Now, what a graph-based
model training is,
is that you use something say like
Tensorflow, Pytorch, MXNET, Dask,
some sort of a distributed library, okay?
What these libraries do is they
build a Directed Acyclic Graph
off of your entire pipeline, right?
So it would put all your preprocessing
functions, your model functions,
your optimization functions,
your loss calculation functions,
all in like one graph, okay?
And it would help you
get that graph, optimize that graph
for your entire architecture, for
your entire cluster architecture.
And then run your training jobs.
What this effectively does is it would
help you optimize all the nooks and crooks
in your entire architecture
before it actually starts training
and second, this way you can
run it on multiple different machines.
So, you can effectively achieve
parallelism in some tasks as well, right?
And that's where a lot of like
Tensorflow, Pytorch stuff helps, right?
And that's what, if you
remember in the first slide,
that's what we were discussing as well,
when we were running multiple--
the same task on multiple worker nodes.
It was quite easy. Why?
Because it-- the overall code was written
as a directed acyclic graph.
So it was already compiled, and
then like-- all that was happening
was it was executing on
different, different GPUs
and that's why we
were getting a speedup.
But more on this later, and in fact,
I have a working session just discussing
these in detail as well.
Now-- now comes the
million-dollar question, right?
How do we build these
scalable ML workflows, given
whatever knowledge we have?
So, I would say there's
something for everyone.
Let's talk about, like in
this particular area, right?
There are generally
just two scenarios, right?
First scenario is wherein
you as a data scientist
or as a machine learning
engineer, you have written code
in say scikit-learn, Statsmodels
XGBoost, and the likes of it
and you're very well aware about building
machine learning workflows on that.
That will be scenario one.
Scenario two is--
and again, assuming that you
already have a pipeline written in
you know, all of this.
Scenario two is when you're
starting an experiment from scratch.
When you're building a machine
learning model from scratch.
In those scenarios, you're free
to choose a particular framework.
You're free to choose say--
Tensorflow, you're free to choose,
you know, something like that.
What you would typically do in both
of these scenarios is something like this.
Wherein you already have, say
for example--
if you already have an entire pipeline,
like in an existing setup
if you already have a machine learning
pipeline written in scikit-learn
or say in XGBoost or some
sort of a library like that,
then you wouldn't want to like--
recreate that library, right?
You would want to make sure
your entire code is maintainable
and you want to make
minimal changes to it.
In those particular scenarios,
what you could do is something
which is put on the left,
is, you can use Dask
for creating batches of your data
and then building
like incremental pipelines,
either using Dask ML
or using scikit-learn.
Both of them are pretty interoperable
and you can use them
to build your distributed pipeline.
And this way you don't have to make a
lot of changes into your existing workflow
and you would also get some
sort of benefits off of distribution
and out of code ML into your pipeline.
Second is a scenario wherein
you are starting from scratch
and you're like, you know, building
an experiment from the get-go.
In those scenarios, I generally
recommend going with the-- you know,
either Tensorflow or Pytorch or
MXNet, one of these libraries wherein
you can effectively create an end-to-end
architecture and the library itself
would create a dag for you and then you
can, you know, use different, different
distribution strategies across your
cluster to be able to build those models.
And those are, again,
like very easy to maintain.
The only thing is it will take some
bit of time for you
if you're new to it
to get a hang of it, right?
And again, now, like with Tensorflow 2.2,
there are like multiple new APIs
that have been introduced.
Like, for example, df.data,
df.distribution strategy, df.--
it supports both either execution and also
like the lazy load execution, wherein you
create the entire graph and then
run it and, you know,
that's I think the way to go
if you have new experiments to run.
Now, enough talk. Let's code.
So now that we've gone through
such a detailed demo about
both Tensorflow as well as Dask, you
may have a question about which one,
which framework, or which flow should you
use for your next machine learning project
or for, you know, taking
on or sort of maintaining
your existing machine learning
workflow or something like that.
Truth be told, this is one quote by
Thomas Sowell, which I follow to the code,
which is that, “There are no solutions,
there are only tradeoffs.”
For example, if you were to
build something with Dask,
then you're stuck with possibly
less parallelizable code, right?
Whereas if you were to build
something with Tensorflow,
then you're stuck with
a very huge learning curve
in terms of learning Tensorflow,
its numerous APIs, not to mention
different sublibraries
for image, for text, for audio
and all those other that it comes with.
Also, keeping in mind that the overall
Tensorflow, Pytorch, Dask, all of this
this entire family is something
which is rapidly evolving as well, right?
So, you have to keep
yourself up to date on that.
However, one, quick thing that I
would say is, and which we have covered
before as well-- remember
the two scenarios?
And there's something
which I always put out is
if you already have a machine
learning workflow,
which is written say in scikit-Learn
or say in Dask,
and you want to extend it to work on
possibly larger set of data,
then you should possibly
look into using Dask ML.
Because you don't have to
rewrite from scratch.
You can use the existing pipeline,
albeit make some changes here and there,
and you're good to go.
Your pipeline works on
a much larger chunk of data then.
However, if you were to build something
from scratch and you know for a fact
that you'll be using-- big data, again,
relative to whatever cluster
or whatever machine
you're running your data in,
you may want to use Tensorflow from
the scratch or you may want to use
say-- Pytorch from the scratch.
I prefer Tensorflow to be honest--
but that helps you big scalability right
from the scratch into your project.
So, that's what my recommendation
would be, and again, do go through
the links to the Colab notebooks
that I just showed a while back.
You can easily retrofit those
to work with your data sets
and try them out for yourself as well.
With that, thank you so
much for attending my talk.
I hope I added some value
to your knowledge base
and you learned something out of it.
Again, you can reach out to me for
any questions at either @reach_vb.
You can find my previous
talks at vaibhav.blog,
and I look forward to hearing from you.
Thank you so much.