Hi, I'm Nina Zakharenko
Some of you might follow
me on Twitter @NNJA.
And I'm here today to show you how to
light up your life with Python and LEDs.
Who am I?
I work at Microsoft as a
Python developer advocate,
and I focus on making Azure and VS code
better to use for Python
developers everywhere.
I've written software for over a decade
at companies like Meetup, Reddit and HBO.
My background is in software,
but I've been working on hardware
as a hobby for the past few years.
If you want to reach out,
please follow me on Twitter
@NNJA or Twitch @NNJA.IO.
And I'm also happy to share that
I'm a newly elected board member
of the Python software foundation.
Now, I want to tell you that software
doesn't have to be serious.
I used to have a lot of creative
energy when I was younger
and an interest in
computers from my young age,
I thought I gave up on all of that
when I joined the workforce
or nobody would take me
seriously as a developer.
I feel like my first few jobs
really sucked the creativity out of me.
I was working for some large enterprises
and financial institutions
and my opportunities for creative
coding really faded away.
I slowly built that back up
by working on Opensource.
Tinkering with hardware was what
really let my creativity explode.
And it's taken me a few years to reconnect
with that part of myself
and relearn the lesson
that I learned all of those years ago,
That software doesn't have to be serious.
You can use code to make art like this.
This is a Python version
of a processing sketch by SaSkia Freeke.
And hardware doesn't have
to be serious either,
this is Simone Giertz.
she's an incredible maker
and a queen of robots,
and she makes very,
very silly contraptions.
This is one of my own creations
and it is inspired by a
project by Sophy Wong.
It's an LED jacket,
but I made a version that I
can control with Bluetooth
so I can change the colors
of the LEDs with my phone
because making something like
this is really fun for me,
it let me create a physical
manifestation of my code.
I really love the idea of LEDs
of making cool wearable projects.
I wanted to make pretty things
that fit my own aesthetic,
which is what got me
interested in hardware in the first place.
And I've really been inspired
by amazing shared projects
and docs from other makers
like Becky Stern and Sophy Wong.
And I made this jacket with LEDs.
I programmed it in CircuitPython
and I'm really not an
expert in electronics.
I never studied it in school
and you don't have to be either
to make projects like this.
Python on hardware.
Earlier I mentioned,
you might've heard of Arduino
code which is a C++ variant,
which unfortunately it's
not very easy to learn.
It's very error prone.
We as a community know from experience
that Python is the opposite.
It's easy to learn.
It's beginner friendly and
it's great for education.
In fact, it was announced
in January of last year
that Python was gonna be the
official programming language
for high school education in France.
How do we go about programming
Python on hardware?
At the moment we have two options.
We have MicroPython and CircuitPython.
MicroPython is a variant of Python 3
that is optimized to
run on microcontrollers.
It's very compact.
It's what runs on the micro:bit.
CircuitPython is an
education friendly fork
of a MicroPython that is
maintained by Adafruit.
I'm gonna be showing you
demos on Adafruit hardware
and so we're gonna be
using CircuitPython today.
These are a few other
devices that run Python.
The BBC micro:bit which
is a computing device
aimed at learning that runs MicroPython.
There's the Adafruit M0 &
M4 that runs CircuitPython
and then the Raspberry Pi Zero W
which is a small development
kit with wireless
and Bluetooth capabilities
runs Python as well.
Depending on where and where
you purchased your hardware,
it might come with Python
installed by default,
it might not.
I'm gonna be showing you a
device that I really like
that is focused on education called
the Adafruit circuit playground express.
It's I think a great
option for an introduction
to electronics and programming hardware.
As a learning platform the cost,
at least in the U.S. is only about $25.
Now Python has this batteries
included philosophy.
There's PEP206 that says,
the Python source
distribution has maintained
a philosophy of batteries included,
which means having a rich and
versatile standard library,
which is immediately available
without making the user
download separate packages.
I think that this has helped
drive Python's success.
Now the circuit playground
express that I'm gonna show you
doesn't actually come with batteries,
but I imagine that the
same philosophy applies.
It has everything that you
need to get started programming
with hardware included on one board,
So just a quick tour of what's on it.
There are 10 Neo pixel RGB LEDs,
each one can display 16 million colors.
There is a light sensor,
temperature sensor,
some programmable buttons
on the left and the right,
a switch, an accelerometer
to detect motion.
There's a micro USB Jack which
makes it easy to program.
And best of all, there is no soldering
required to access these features,
which is great for kids
or for clumsy adults.
You can easily connect other things
to it with alligator clips.
You can even sew on it
with conductive thread.
Now I'm gonna be showing you
some live demos from my desk today.
I actually have a circuit
playground express with me.
So this is the one that is on my desk
and I have it right here
and I'll be showing
you some demos shortly.
So we talked about the LEDs.
How do we light up the LEDs that are
on the front of this device?
Well, there's an important concept
that you need to know about RGB LEDs.
An RGB LED is really a combination of
three tiny LEDs in just one package.
RGB stands for red, green, and blue.
And if you look at the color
wheel on the right hand side,
you can see that you can
produce almost any color
by combining these three colors
in intensity is varying from zero to 255.
Now zero means that the
color is not present.
For example, blue is set to 255,
red set to zero and green set to zero
would produce pure blue.
By combining the
intensities of these colors,
you can produce 16
million color variations.
Now, I didn't fully understand this
until I found this picture of an RGB LED
in action under a microscope.
So let's take a quick look at that.
Here's the tiny RGB LED.
There are three LEDs present
in each one of these;
red, green, and blue.
These three tiny LEDs
can light up one by one
or altogether or a combination,
but because they're so small,
your eye actually sees them as one color.
In this picture, the initial
picture they're all off.
Here's a photo with just one LED on.
This is the red LED.
You can tell the color
that is gonna appear
by the color of the outside ring.
So in this case, it is red.
Here is just the green LED that is lit
and just the blue LED that's lit.
When all of them are turned on,
the LED is gonna look white to your eye.
And depending on the
combinations of colors,
it can look like all the
different colors in between.
Know that Neo pixel is
the Adafruit brand name
for an individually addressable LED
that's commonly known as the WS2812.
Now, how do we program it?
This is a lot easier than working
with Arduino based platforms.
If you've worked with Arduino in the past,
you have to unplug and reset the board
and it's kind of tedious.
With CircuitPython, you
can just plug in the device
with a data and charge USB cable,
and you'll see a
CircuitPython drive on Mac.
It will be in VOLUMES/CIRCUITPY.
If you don't see it there,
you can install
CircuitPython on the device.
Once you have done that,
you can create or edit a code.py
file in the root directory
and every time you save it,
it's gonna get automatically
reloaded to the device.
So it's a really quick and easy workflow.
I like programming with visual studio code
and the Python extension
which is what I'm gonna
be showing you today.
But what you really need to know
is you can use any editor that you like,
but you need to use an editor
that writes up the file
completely when you save it.
And there are other really good options
available for programming
hardware in Python
if you're more of a beginner
or you're less familiar with Python.
The Mu editor is a great option.
What happens if you
don't have the hardware?
Adafruit is based in New York
for a while earlier this year,
they weren't shipping.
Maybe this hardware is
difficult to get in Korea.
Well, some interns at Microsoft
released a really cool project
called the device simulator
express extension.
So you can use this to
simulate a few platforms
like the micro:bit, the
circuit playground express
and even the Adafruit clipboard
and I'm gonna be showing you
a short demo of this today.
And there's a link in the slides
to download the extension
that's available here.
If you want to take a look at the slides
there at nina.to/pykr2020.
One more option for
programming these boards.
If you want to get start
at programming hardware
with zero coding and
without the device itself,
there's something called
Microsoft MakeCode.
It's a block-based editor.
You can export it as JavaScript.
There's some really cool collaborations
like with cartoon network
and you don't need to have the hardware.
It's an emulator.
You can see what's happening right away.
I think this drag and drop interface
is really simple to understand for kids
or for folks who might not necessarily
be familiar with programming.
It can make them productive very quickly.
Let's take a look at some simple code
that's for the circuit playground express.
First, we import the library as CPX.
Next, we make a color variable for red,
remember RGB.
So I'm setting 255 for the red position,
zero for the green position,
zero for the blue position.
And I'm also setting the brightness down
because otherwise by
default, it's very bright.
Now we want to keep looping forever,
not just running our code once.
You want to think of it as an animation.
If you just run it once,
your LED would blink red
and then it would turn off right away.
So if you want to keep the red color on,
you need to loop forever.
And we're using a
cpx.pixels.fill helper method
to fill all the pixels on
the board with one color.
Now this library also exposes
some of the different
components on this board.
So in this case,
we have button A and button
B that's on the board.
We can access them with
cpx.button_a and cpx.button_b.
And those variables will be set to true
when the button is pressed
and false when it's not.
So let's take a look at this
code in the VS code emulator
or VS code device simulator express.
So I would need to open
my VS code command palette
and since I already have the device
simulator express extension installed,
you would have to go ahead
and install that first.
And then when we go to our code,
I can open my command palette and say,
Device simulator express: Run simulator.
And it'll show us a little diagram of
the circuit playground express
here on the right hand side.
So if we look at this code,
we'll see that if we press button A,
the pixel should fill with red.
So let's try that.
If we hover the mouse over here,
we'll see that button A is highlighted.
So when we press button A,
the pixels are filled with red.
Otherwise if we press button B,
the pixels are filled with the color blue.
If neither of the buttons are pressed,
then we don't fill the LEDs with anything,
we just keep them off,
which is pretty cool.
Let's look at some code
that's a little bit more complicated.
Here's a simple program
that's gonna cycle through
red, green and blue with button presses
and let's walk through this one by one.
So first I'm importing the
two libraries that I'm using;
the circuit playground
express library and time.
And I'm setting up some
colors that I'm gonna be using
in my code; red, green, and blue.
Again, notice where the
zero and the 255s are,
then I'm gonna make a
list of all the colors
that I want to loop through,
starting in a position of zero.
Again, instead of running our code once,
so it doesn't stop after the first time,
we're gonna loop forever
and we're gonna constantly
be checking for input.
So I'm gonna be filling the LEDs
on the circuit playground
express with the selected color.
And then if button A
or button B is pressed,
I'm going to flip over to the next color
and then I'm gonna sleep
for just a fifth of a second
to prevent multiple button presses.
So let's take a look at
what this looks like.
Now for this demo, I'm
gonna close the simulator
because I'm gonna be showing you
on the actual circuit playground express
that is on my desktop right here.
So taking a look at this,
I'll see that I have a CIRCUITPY folder
and I'm gonna open code.py
which is what is currently
running on this device.
So as you'll see, the LEDs are red.
Now, if I press the button,
it should switch to green and
then it should switch to blue.
Red, green, blue
each time I press the button.
It doesn't matter which button I press.
Let's change our code a little bit.
Let's take a look at our color chart
and let's add a new color to this list.
For this example, I want to pick yellow,
which is a mix of red and green.
So I'm gonna make a new variable, yellow.
Remember I'm gonna set 255 for red,
255 for green and zero
for blue to make yellow
and then I'm gonna add yellow to my list.
Now that I have saved,
my code should be on this
device already, automatically.
I don't have to do anything special.
So let's test it out and see if it works.
I'm switching over to green,
switching over to blue,
and now one more button
press and now I have yellow.
So the code to make this
was pretty straight forward.
I'm not the only one that
thinks hardware is really cool.
90% of students said that the micro:bit
showed them that anyone can code.
86% of surveyed students
said the micro:bit
made computer science more interesting.
But something that's near and dear to me
is that 70% more girls surveyed
said they would choose
computing as a school subject
after using the micro:bit.
There was a study called
unlocking the clubhouse
that suggested that
traditional computing culture
is a boys club and it's
unfriendly to women
and we need to find ways to unlock
this clubhouse to make it accessible.
There was a study on E-textiles
called LilyPad in the wild,
which suggested a different approach
called building new clubhouses.
Instead of trying to fit people
into existing engineering cultures,
it may be more constructive
to try to spark
and support new cultures
to build new clubhouses
and make room for more diverse
interests and passions.
And remember that diversity
doesn't stop at gender.
We want to use Python on hardware
to encourage everyone to participate,
people of different ethnicities
and socio-economic status
identity is neurodiversity,
age and many other factors.
So let's make Python on hardware
the most diverse community that we can.
The hardware community is really awesome
about sharing incredible projects
with step by step instructions.
Some of the places that
you might find these is
Adafruit guides, Microsoft
MakeCode or Instructables.
On the left is a jack-o-lantern project
where you only need the
circuit playground board
and a Ziploc bag if you
opt to for a real pumpkin.
Python on hardware is
still relatively new,
so don't forget to
share your own projects.
Angela Sheehan is a maker
that I really look up to.
She created these incredible
LED high heel shoes and a lot more.
So just one more example
of making new clubhouses.
How cool are these?
The nature of hardware is being able
to see these instantaneous results.
More importantly, being able
to customize your projects
helps you connect to them from the start.
It helps make technology more accessible
to those who are traditionally
underrepresented in it.
This picture of girls with huge
beaming smiles is one of my favorites.
They're made by girls participants
that made LEDs light up in masks.
So E-textiles, Sobel
electronics, paper crafts,
these all help to introduce technology
in new and unexpected ways.
I'm wearing one of my
favorite projects on camera.
This is based on a different
Adafruit Python board,
the Gemma M0 and some LED rings.
It's based on an original
design by Becky Stern.
Let's see if I can get these to turn on.
My earings that are on
right now, run Python,
which I absolutely love.
You can check out the code
on Github if you would like.
And I wanted to say that
you've seen that Python
opens up this whole new world
of working with hardware.
Lawrence Durell said that,
"Our inventions mirror our secret wishes."
So hopefully this inspires
you to try it out on your own.
Next steps for you if you have
or have access to a
circuit playground express,
that's a great first start.
If you don't,
you can still learn about
the concepts of hardware
with Microsoft MakeCode with
the device simulator express.
I hope that I've shown you
that you don't necessarily
need to be an expert
or know a lot about electronics
to just get started.
And please write your code,
but also share it with the community,
follow our community guide
and learn, make things,
create and teach others.
It's a really fantastic cycle of that
we can all participate in.
If you want to share your projects,
you can use the Python hardware hashtag
on Twitter to get started.
Thank you all so much.
It's really been my pleasure
being able to speak to PyCon
Korea remotely this year.
I hope that I've left you inspired
and that you've learned how
to program LEDs with Python
to light up your own life
with code and creativity.
The slides will be
posted at the link here:
nina.to/pykr2020
and thank you all so much.