Hi everyone, this session is titled,
"g0v.py g0vernance.txt".
My name is Chihhao Yu
and I'm from Taiwan.
I'm a g0v contributor.
First of all, these slides
are publicly available on the Internet,
so if you go to the URL here,
you can just see
the slides for yourself.
These slides are also open source,
it's released under a CC license.
Here are a list of contributors.
And before we begin,
there's a warning
that says personal perspectives
do not represent g0v as a whole.
I'll explain more later,
but because g0v is a community,
not an organization,
so, everyone stands for themselves,
everyone speaks for themselves.
Let me introduce
a little bit about g0v,
which is the name of our community.
g0v is spelled, G-Zero-V.
The name came from
the word, "Government"
G-O-V, but replaced
the O with a zero,
meaning either start over,
start from zero,
or digitization of government.
This is a Taiwanese movement
started from 2012.
And it has been very active
until now, actually.
The g0v community has a manifesto
and it describes what
it is in the document.
So, I'll try to adapt from the g0v manifesto
and summarize it for you,
and tell you what g0v
is in my own perspective.
So, g0v is a polycentric
community in Taiwan
that uses open-source technology
and open collaboration to
better government and society.
Every slide would have sources
that links to the sources,
the references that's used in a slide.
So, here you can see
a Mandarin version
of the manifesto,
and also an English version
of the manifesto linked in the slides.
So, what this means is g0v is a community
that has a lot of centers.
These centers include projects
or task forces.
And each of these centers,
these projects, these task forces,
will decide what they want to do
for themselves.
And each one of these centers
would collaborate together.
And g0v's main methods are
using open-source technology
and open collaboration,
and the goal is to
better government and society.
So, today, since
it's PyCon Korea,
the organizers have asked me to introduce
some examples of g0v projects
that use Python
in the past and in present.
So, as the title of
this session suggests,
I'd like to introduce to you
some g0v projects that used Python.
So, after a little digging, actually,
Python was there from the very beginning
of the g0v community.
So, I would like to introduce
to you some a group of projects
that falls under four categories:
Open government,
open data, education,
and media literacy.
And, of course, there are many, many
more projects in the g0v community.
But today, because of time,
there's only so much
we can discuss.
The first one is actually,
the first project of the g0v community,
which is TW Budget,
which stands for
Taiwanese government budget,
it is one of the first
projects that's produced by g0v-ers,
or which is how we call ourselves
g0v contributors.
It is a project that visualizes
Taiwan's central government budget.
And since this is a Web version
of the presentation,
I can just go to the Web page
and show you, live,
how this project will work.
As you see,
this is an interactive
visualization of our
central government's budget.
If you click, you can actually
know more detail of each--
each of these budget items
corresponding to some government agencies,
big or small.
Because of humor, which is a very
important component of the g0v community,
this Website also converts
every item of the budget into
cups of bubble tea or
slices of chicken,
to sort of represent how much,
how big the budget item is.
The second project that I would like
to talk to you about is a voter guide.
Voter's guide is a voter's guide, which
is a list of information
of candidates for Taiwan’s both
local and national elections.
Voter's guide is a very old project in the
g0v community.
It started in 2014, I think, if I'm not
remembering--
if I'm remembering correctly.
It has undergone several iterations
and this is the 2020 version.
If you can see, this is a link
to all the legislative candidates here,
grouped by cities or counties
here in Taipei.
You see all the candidates
that was participating in the election
and if you click into them,
you see some of their information,
including which of the
legislations they've supported
including how much
Facebook ads they have--
they have put out on Facebook.
And then we have projects for open data.
The first one, this one, is also very old.
It's ER Dashboard.
ER stands for emergency rooms.
This is a dashboard of all
the emergency rooms in Taiwan, showing
how many patients are
in each of these rooms
and how many beds are available,
for example.
This one, this project, Rentea
is a newer project in the g0v community.
It is about rental housing info in Taiwan.
And all of these projects use
Python in various ways,
including in front-end, back-end
but most of them use Python
for data processing.
This one is pronounced 'Moh-wet dict'.
MoE Dict.
This is a dictionary, an open-source
dictionary that is also a very old project
in Tai-- sorry, in the g0v community.
And this is a combination of a lot of
different government and academic sources
to combine into one open-sourced dictionary
online for people to use.
And if you see here, this is
the MoE Dict Website.
This is a term that says, "The best"--
or "The brightest."
And this is the Mandarin version
of the phrase
and these are the Taiwanese version,
the English version,
even French and German.
And because this-- because this
is open source, it also
allows people to collectively correct it,
if there is any mistake.
Another project is iTaigi,
which, in Taiwanese,
means 'love Taiwanese'.
Taiwanese is our local language here.
Quite different from Mandarin,
which is sort of a standardized language.
This is-- this is a website
for you to learn
different pronunciations
of Taiwanese terms.
You can actually listen to the
pronunciation on the Website.
It also has-- it also has
interesting features,
like how to pronounce your name
or how to pronounce Pokemon monsters.
And that was an educational project,
and the final category
I want to talk about
is a media literacy project.
This one is called News Diff.
As the name suggests, this project--
records or archives news articles,
but also detects changes over time.
This is the website of the project.
You see, each item is a news article,
and the system automatically detects
the first-- the first instance
of the article when it's published,
but also subsequent changes
in the article,
both in the title or in the content.
So, it's very useful
if you want to do further analysis
on news coverage here in Taiwan.
Another project I want
to talk to you about is Cofacts.
Cofacts is a crowd-sourced,
fact-checking platform and a line bot.
What this means is that it's
a line bot, as in people can send
suspicious information to
Cofacts database.
It's a crowd-sourced,
fact-checking platform,
as in people can collectively
come together
and fact check those messages together,
and publish the results
into Cofacts’ database,
so that the original user who submitted
the message will receive them.
This is Cofacts' Website.
And you can see how it works.
You forward suspicious information
to the line bot
and then if the database contains it,
you will receive fact-checking results.
If the database doesn't have it,
then you can also join
the fact-checking efforts.
Another project is Oarchive.
This is very new in the g0v community.
This is an effort to archive
not only just the news websites,
but all kinds of different
information here in Taiwan,
including some of the more
suspicious ones like content farms,
but also Taiwan's local Web forums,
like PTT or dcard.
These-- these media literacy projects
all have open data, which means
it's very useful to
researchers and academics
who want to do this kind of research.
So, there are a lot of
projects in g0v community.
And why are there so many projects?
A big component of the g0v projects--
sorry, the g0v community is food.
The g0v community hosts hack-a-thons
every now and then, and every hack-a-thon
would have a lot of pizza,
a lot of fried chicken,
a lot of drinks, and also desserts.
And sometimes, these foods are themed
to make it more interesting.
So, these events and this food--
these foods is a very important component
that supports the entire community,
and what you might
call infrastructure of the community.
And-- we just saw many projects
in g0v community
that's using Python to do
all sorts of things
like open data, like media literacy.
But you can also use Python to build up
infrastructure of a community.
So, I'd like to talk to you about this.
Two major functions of infrastructure
in a community:
One is to connect
and the other one is to discover.
Because the g0v community is such
a polycentric, or decentralized,
or distributed community,
and there is a lot of different things
and different places
that you might not know
about as a g0v contributor,
or as an outsider who wants
to know more about g0v.
So, important features of infrastructure is
to connect a lot of different projects,
and different people,
maybe into one place,
maybe into a GitHub repo.
So you can see a list of all kinds
of things that happen in the g0v community.
Another important function
of the infrastructure
is to discover, is for you to--
discover things that you're interested in,
in the community, despite its--
decentralized nature.
So, for example, you can use Python
and people have used--
g0v contributors have used Python
to, for example, collect information
on GitHub repos, or GitHub issues.
But people have also used Python
to build a search interface
for all kinds of things g0v related.
This is the search interface on g0v's
official Website.
If you search, for example, COVID,
you will see a lot of different things.
This page is full of chat log
and there's more chat log.
And there's more chat log.
So, this is an example of using Python
to build up infrastructure
for the community.
So, I think infrastructure for g0v
is also infrastructure for polycentrism,
which is infrastructure to support
this kind of distributed community.
There are a lot of times when people ask,
"Why is g0v decentralized?"
Or, "Why is g0v polycentric?"
It's a very important question,
and a very interesting one.
Everyone has their own opinion,
and everyone has their own perspective
when answering this question.
What I think is why is g0v polycentric
is because democracy is also polycentric.
In a democracy, like South Korea
or Taiwan,
there are a lot
of different kinds of people,
and people have all kinds
of different opinions.
And people form different groups,
different organizations,
different networks, and every different
networks or different groups
does different things, and because we
have basic freedoms, civic liberties,
we're doing
what we want to do,
and we have the freedom to associate,
we have the freedom to assemble,
and we have the freedom of speech.
And these kind of values, these values
are the values that
the g0v community supports.
So, what I think is g0v
could be seen as a mini version.
or a shadow version of
the larger democracy or
society that we live in today.
And g0v is also a very good place to
discuss or even experiment
different kinds of democratic methods.
So a community like g0v
is very decentralized or polycentric,
which also means that
it needs policies and mechanisms
to protect
or to support its polycentrism.
I think a community like g0v
needs policies and mechanisms
to maintain its polycentric nature
to prevent abuse--
to express its many selves
meaning everyone is
everyone is a g0v contributor.
And everyone sort of reflects different
characteristics of the community.
The community also needs
policies and mechanisms to grow
and to evolve into
whatever the contributor wants it to go.
So, these kind of policies and mechanisms
could also be seen
as a part of infrastructure.
And although it's not Python,
it's not written in Python,
it's still kind of a code.
Maybe it's policies, general concepts,
also maybe it's just
very concrete rules that
defines how things are done,
and what other things are not allowed.
This is why the second part of the title
of this session is, "g0vernance.txt".
Although g0vernance is not
actual runnable code
the computer might not know it,
but people certainly know how to read,
and how to set up, and how to challenge
these kinds of code.
So, I'd like to talk to you about these kinds
of code as a second part of this session.
Like the part before,
I’ve also identified some different
categories when it comes to g0vernance.
Different projects,
some of these projects here
in the g0v community is related to policy.
Some of it is actually
establishing mechanisms for
how things work and
what kind of things are not allowed.
The other kind of project
is to create maps, which means
since g0v is such a big and diverse
community, we need maps to navigate.
We need maps to understand
sort of the whole picture,
or as close to the whole picture as
we could possibly be.
And the final category is 0RG.
This is a play on the organization.
But it's not a top-down
or a hierarchical organization,
as we usually are familiar.
This is an organization that
has g0v’s characteristics,
but also doing concrete actions to sort
of implement the policies and mechanisms,
and try to evolve
and make them better as well.
From the very beginning of the community,
you see a lot of shared
documents that talk about these things.
Here are three examples of early
g0v documents that talk about g0vernance,
in a very philosophical,
but also sometimes very concrete ways.
There are three topics:
Citizenship, media policy,
and foreign policy.
If you just look at foreign policy,
it almost feels like g0v is a
kind of government,
which--actually, was part of the idea
when g0v community was first started--
is to create some kind
of shadow government
in order to supervise the government,
and to better the government,
to show a different
working kind of prototype,
to show that we can govern ourselves
differently, and more efficiently,
and more inclusively.
The first document that we have
is regarding citizenship.
And it talks about how
to talk about yourself as a g0v-er.
In Mandarin, there's different-- different
kinds of terms to describe yourself,
as someone who is connected,
or who is participating,
or who is contributing to the community.
And here is the actual document
that talks about this.
It actually--
it actually just lists out
different kinds of way to
identify yourself as someone
who is connected or who--
who acknowledges the community.
This first one is contributor,
the second one is participant.
And then different kinds of ways
to talk about yourself,
and also lists out the pros and cons
of different ways to identify yourself.
For example, if you say that you are
a member of the g0v community,
the pros are--
it's easily understandable
for other people,
and it creates less confusion
for other people.
But the cons are--
because g0v is a polycentric community
that has very vague borders,
but the term 'member'
just suggests that some people are inside,
some people are outside,
but it's actually
more complicated than that.
The second document is media policy.
Media policy talks about how g0v-ers
go on the media and talk about g0v.
Here is the content of the document.
And it has many suggestions
on what to do and what not to do.
This is the document for foreign policy.
It actually just expands
media policy and talks about
how g0v-ers engage with--
sort of, the world.
Things are-- things that are not communal.
Other hierarchical organizations.
Or other people that have not heard
of g0v and how do we engage with them.
It lists out different ways
of engaging with the world.
This one is a panel discussion.
Maybe a press conference.
How do you-- how do you--
what is the best way to sort of
navigate those situations.
And here is when you are
the point of contact
how do you do that?
This is when you're invited to
give a talk, how do you do that?
And--
Yeah. It’s very interesting to
read these early documents to
look at how early on g0v contributors
think about these issues.
And these issues also
persists in the community.
People still think about them
and all kinds of different mechanisms
are still being evolved, or being changed
as we speak.
There's two examples here
I'd like to provide that actually set up
concrete mechanisms for g0vernance.
The first one is the amendments,
or how to amend the g0v communi--
Sorry, the g0v manifesto.
Remember the-- one of the first
ideas we talked about in the g0v manifesto
is how g0v describes itself.
So what happens if g0v
evolves and the description
when it was founded no longer fits
the current situation?
It's sort of like, how do we
amend our constitution when--
things have changed, when time has passed,
when the situation
is very different from before.
So, in October 20th, 2019
some g0v-ers actually came up
with a procedure of how to amend
our manifesto.
The central idea is that anyone
can propose an amendment to the manifesto.
And there are also
some conditions regarding
how do you propose an amendment.
It has to be proposed
in the big hack-a-thons
that g0v community hosts
every two months.
It has to have a host
of this proposal, meaning that
one person has to be the point of contact
of this proposal.
And it has to have
open documents that anyone can read
about the proposal and
how it's being discussed in--
in the hack-a-thon
and also in follow-up meetings.
And once the proposal is finalized,
it has to have a public review period
of two weeks.
And it has to the link of the proposal
has to be posted in g0v's Slack
for as many people to see as possible.
And if there's no opposing opinions
in two weeks,
then the proposal is adopted
and it becomes sort of the new manifesto.
And if there are opposing ideas,
or opinions, then we would resolve
to general discussion in the general channel
of g0v's Slack.
So this kind of
procedure is very important
because it lists out exact steps
of the g0vernance.
It's not vague ideas or
vague, abstract concept.
It's actually-- it's actually
something that you can follow
and go through and, you know,
this is a checklist,
so it's very easy to see where
each of these proposals
is in terms of their progress.
So this is actually the final version
that has been proposed on October 20th
and it was passed
two weeks later on November 4th.
It amends the original manifesto
into its current form.
So, this document also provides
some history of the original manifesto
and the changes underneath this.
And a log of all kinds of discussions
that happened during the hack-a-thon
and also during follow-up meetings.
One of the interesting points that
happened during this discussion
is the phrase, 'liquid democracy'.
When g0v was first founded
the idea of liquid democracy actually
excites a lot of people.
And it was in the mani-- it was
put inside the original manifesto.
But over time, we realized
the difficulties of the liquid democracy
and in the current form of the manifesto,
this term no longer exists.
The other interesting part is about
freedom of speech, or freedom of expression.
And there are-- there are talks about
if freedom of expression is
actually the best way,
or the best phrase to describe
what we support fundamentally.
But then, the term actually--
well, after a period of
discussion, the term actually--
the people have decided
that this term actually
is still the best way to
describe what we think here,
so it was put--
it was kept unchanged.
So, this is a very good example
for me to see,
while g0v has fundamental ideas as foundations
or infrastructure as the community,
it's also very adaptable
and it's also very open
and transparent when people
when people propose change.
Open discussions are facilitated
and different ideas are considered.
This sort of for me, in a way,
manifests g0v's own beliefs in itself,
which is very interesting
and very good to me, I think.
The second example is
how the g0v community
governs its social media platforms.
And as you might know,
g0v has a official--
Facebook account, Facebook page, actually.
So, the question,
the concrete question is
who gets to post what
on g0v's Facebook page?
So, this has been very vague
for some time.
And some time last year,
some g0v-ers, including myself,
decided to come together
and discuss if we can set up
a concrete checklist-style mechanism
for all g0v contributors to follow
and while not make
the g0v Facebook page
the tool for a minority of
the g0v contributor,
but actually anyone can propose a post
to be posted.
So, this is the final mechanism
that was discussed and decided.
And we have decided that
there will be a group of reviewers
that reviews every post that's been
proposed to be posted.
And fundamentally, what's important
is that all the proposals
and all the discussions
has to take place
in public spaces.
In public channels on Slack,
or in public shared documents
like Google Docs or HackMD,
so that it remains transparent.
We have also decided--
The g0vernance mechanism or model
of the reviewer group--
Who gets to be a reviewer?
Anyone can say that he or she
or they want to be a reviewer.
And if two people agree, they can join
the reviewer group and become a reviewer.
We have also discussed the review period,
meaning how long does a post
have to be reviewed before it's posted?
So, this is a very concrete and
and something that could be practiced
in reality.
And this mechanism has actually been
heavily enforced
during the past couple of months
because right now, the g0v community
is preparing for its summit
at the end of this year
and because of the promotional
needs of the summit,
there were a lot of posts being proposed
to the reviewers to be posted,
And the workload spiked
and produced a lot of workload
for the reviewers.
And that was a challenge
for this mechanism.
And perhaps there will be a discussion of
how to make it more efficient in the future.
But the important thing is--
the important thing is all this--
all these discussions are transparent
and open to anyone to see and participate.
So, that it doesn't become
closed off and abused by some people,
rather the other.
So, let's go back to the slides.
The other type of project is map.
This is a very difficult
kind of project to do
because g0v is so diverse and
is so decentralized.
No one actually knows how big it is.
For example, we know that on
g0v's Slack, there are
more or less eight thousand accounts.
But we never know the exact number of
people who would identify
as g0v-ers, for example.
And we have never known the exact numbers
of projects that's in the g0v community.
That's why people have done things like
aggregating repo info,
or aggregating issue info.
People have done multiple project hubs
to try to aggregate all--
all the projects
of the g0v community, but
it was a very difficult project to do.
And so is the map.
This is something I attempted
less than two years ago, in 2018.
I was trying to think of
different projects that I know
in the g0v community and try to
create a map of how they overlap.
And this map was created.
It was very chaotic.
It's quite difficult to read,
so this is a very early draft
of what a map could look like.
And because g0v is decentralized,
everyone could create their own maps.
And maybe there's a way
to collectivize these results
and create a more inclusive map
from different perspectives.
And the final example that I want
to share with you is organizations,
or groups, or task forces,
as we call them,
that practice these
g0vernance models or mechanisms.
There are more than one of these groups,
but the one I have been participating
is called g0v International.
This is a fairly new task force--
that was established
in the end of 2018.
Sorry, the end of 2019.
What we were concerning was the g0vernance
Of g0v's international affairs.
Since g0v was founded in 2012,
because there were a lot of projects
alot of contributors of the g0v movement
people from outside Taiwan
started to notice the
community and started to reach out,
and trying to establish
different kinds of relationships.
g0v-ers were invited to give talks,
g0v-ers were invited to collaborate
with outside organizations outside Taiwan.
Some other chances are people want
to fund certain g0v projects
these all kinds of
international exchanges or affairs
really touches the center of what we
just talked about g0vernance of a community.
At its core, I think, it's the question:
who gets to represent the community
when reaching out to the
international community?
So, g0v International is a new task force
that's established
to think about this problem
because there are a lot of different
problems that we think of every day,
but if there's no
people inside the project
to think of it constantly,
there will not be progress.
So, because I think
about g0vernance a lot,
so I participated
in this task force to think of
to think about this problem together
with other g0v-ers.
And one thing that we
feel strongly is that
rather than doing international
exchanges through conferences,
by giving talks,
giving keynote addresses,
what we think might be a better way to do
these exchanges is
to host hack-a-thons,
international hack-a-thons,
so that it's not so much
as one g0v-er on the stage
representing the entire community,
but it's more about inviting
more than one.
many g0v-er contributors to
come to the event,
and also inviting a lot more
different members
or contributors of different communities
from the international-- from the world
to come together in a hack-a-thon
and actually talk about projects,
and actually work together on projects.
So, this is one thing that the g0v
international task force think would--
would more or less alleviate
or lessen the impact of one person
representing the community,
because there are times
when this is necessary--
when talking to
groups or organizations
that doesn't necessarily know what
a polycentric community is.
So, what the g0v International has done
in the past two years is host such events.
The g0v International task force
hosted two hack-a-thons,
along with our partners or our friends
in Japan,
in South Korea, and in Hong Kong.
The first event
was hosted in Okinawa, actually.
We were joking that Okinawa
is sort of the midway between
all these places that we have--
we are collaborating.
It's actually not, but everyone
gets to fly somewhere else,
which is really interesting and attractive
to a lot of us.
We are calling these hack-a-thons
"Facing the Ocean" meet and hacks.
Facing the Ocean is something that we’ve
talked about and discussed together,
between contributors in Taiwan
in Japan, in South Korea, in Hong Kong,
and thinking about
Facing the Ocean,
finding different opportunities
to network together.
And the first one is, as I just said,
it was hosted in Okinawa in June 2019,
and the second one was hosted
in Tainan here in Taiwan,
a southern city of Taiwan,
in December 2019.
And we were scheduling the third one
to be hosted in Jeju Island, South Korea,
this summer, but because of
COVID-19 we're not allowed,
we're not able to do that,
so instead, we've been hosting
online sessions, small or big
trying to keep this network alive,
and exchanges our experiences
in all kinds of things, including how to
fight this pandemic together.
So, in close,
I'd like to share this thought with you
is although there are a lot
of different projects in g0v,
I think my favorite g0v project
is g0v itself.
It's being to see all this diversity,
all its differences,
but also trying to find commonalities
between different projects,
different people.
And thinking about g0vernance might be
really dull for some people, but not to me.
I think about these rules,
these mechanisms a lot,
and these, I think, really is important
to a community that wants
to keep its polycentric nature and
wants to keep it open, wants
to keep things transparent.
So, that's why I decided to accept
the invitation of the organizing team and
come to you and share not only the history
of some projects of the g0v community,
but also g0vernance and how
g0v-ers are handling
this very different and complex
issue together.
So, there is a very common saying
in the g0v community,
which is, "You are nobody."
This comes from a wordplay
in the Mandarin language,
is that nobody-- we often complain,
"Why is nobody doing this?"
But one belief that's very central to
the community is that you are that nobody.
If you see something that nobody's doing,
maybe you're the one
who's supposed to do that.
So in close, I'd like to share this
saying with you,
that all of you are nobody.
Which means that if you see something
that you want in the world,
you are the one to make it happen
and exist in the world
not only just using technology,
not only creating open data,
but other things as well.
People often say that
people often ask,
"If I don't know how to code,
can I participate?
Can I join the community?"
And people always say, "Yes."
You don't need to know coding.
You don't need to be an engineer
to contribute to the g0v community,
or any other kind of community
that's using technology and collaboration
to better government and society.
In g0v, there are a lot of people
who are designers, who are writers,
who are lawyers,
who just doesn't know how to code,
doesn't know how to
write a computer program.
But everyone knows--
but the important thing is
keep the spirit of
open source in your heart
and collaborate in an open manner.
And that way, the community
will thrive and grow with you.
So, here are three links
if you are interested to follow.
One is including
this slides, a lot of these-- I mean,
most of g0v's shared documents live
in this Web service called HackMD.
This is a link for you to check out
all the different kind of documents
that's been composed by g0v-ers.
The second link is for you
to join g0v's Slack.
If you are interested,
come into our chat room and talk to us.
And the third link is actually
if you're even more interested
you are very welcome to
come join us at the end of this year,
December 3rd through
December the 6th,
the g0v Summit 2020, which is
g0v community's biannual gathering.
This year, because of COVID-19,
foreigners might not be able
to attend physically here in Taiwan,
but we are working very hard
to design mechanisms
for people to participate remotely,
including our speakers
and regular participants, attendees.
And this year's g0v Summit
the temporary, or the working theme
is locality and connectivity,
which means that
there are a lot of communities
here in Taiwan, not just g0v,
and there are a lot of
different communities in our region
in Taiwan, in Japan,
in South Korea, in Hong Kong,
and other places here in Asia,
and also across the world.
So, we want to explore
what more can we do when we're connected?
What more can we do when these networks
are built, are maintained,
and are nurtured?
So as one of the co-chairs
of this year's g0v Summit,
I very sincerely invite
and welcome you to come
in December to join us
in g0v Summit 2020.
So, that's my session.
Thank you for listening.
If you have any questions,
come to g0v's Slack and
I'll be there,
and as will be many more
g0v contributors to--
to answer your questions,
to introduce you to different projects,
and yeah, just to talk.
Thank you very much.