Hello, I am Siyoung Oh from the
PyCon Korea Organizing Team
And I am Aven Oh
This year, there is a special session
from the PyCon Korea Organizing Team
We will tell you how we are shaping PyCon
Korea to contribute to the Python ecosystem
Today, we will talk about about the CoC,
which is PyCon Korea's code of conduct
Aven, have you heard of the CoC?
Yes, I have heard of it
I am sure you are all
observing to the CoC as well
The CoC is our promise to
everyone participating in PyCon Korea
PyCon Korea is a community event
Presenters have stepped up
to share their experiences
Sponsors, individual sponsors,
business partners,
and all participants including the
PyCon Korea Organizing Team
who are volunteering the entire year
are voluntarily contributing to the
community, expecting nothing in return
PyCon Korea aims to be an event
in which anyone can easily participate
We aim to create an atmosphere in which
we acknowledge and respect our differences
We encourage a welcoming atmosphere
Such values of PyCon Korea
are embodied in this CoC
To create a Python community
where nobody is excluded
PyCon Korea's CoC is a promise that should
be kept by the members at the very least
All of you, including myself and
Aven here, are keeping this promise
It is kept not just for
the day of the event
but also while preparing for PyCon Korea
and in all of our contents
This is how it is done
Have you imagined an event
where anyone can be involved?
At PyCon Korea, we want all of you
to be respected for who you are
Are you thinking, "Is that even possible?"
or "That's being too idealistic"?
You could think that way
We may not be perfect, but we
are trying and putting in our efforts
while imagining the future
that our efforts will bring
A place where you can feel safe
and have fun talking even with strangers
about Python, which we all have in common
"Sure, this is good enough",
"Everyone's like that"
"I should keep it in" "Am I sensitive?"
Instead of these thoughts
what about a place where you can point out
that something's wrong
without feeling threatened?
A community where I am
respected for who I am
and where everyone feels safe
and can trust each other
A place where we can
all talk about going forward
That's the kind of environment
we are imagining
But Aven,
this is a technology conference
People might wonder why
we are talking so idealistically
Why is it important that we
embrace every participant?
You're right,
and as Siyoung pointed out
this is a technology conference
However, if you ask us why it is so
important that we embrace every participant
this is how we look at it
I think PyCon Korea's attitude
of respecting diversity
is the source that enriches
our society and community
Finding a solution to a problem
and keeping the community growing
in order to change the world for the better
requires diverse experience and perspective
Such diverse experience and perspective
begin from respecting and
embracing each other
That's what we think
The CoC is a promise for everyone
The CoC is always evolving
to create a better community
It wasn't made to criticize
or exclude anyone
It also isn't a perfect set of rules
to determine if someone's wrong
That's right, as Siyoung just said
the CoC isn't a set of rules to
criticize or exclude someone
nor is it perfect
However, we are trying things one at a time
so that our efforts seep through everywhere
One of them is the CoC Agreement
like the one you see below
At PyCon Korea, when presenters
make their presentations
or when our business partners work with us
or when our sponsors support us
or when someone becomes a member
of the PyCon Korea Organizing Team
we sign an agreement like
the one you see below
We also observe the CoC for presentations
When making presentation proposals or
reviewing videos of presentation materials
we check to see if the CoC
has been observed
Although it is unfortunate
we can't see them this year
you can easily find signs on the CoC
at the offline site of our event
This is how we're creating
an environment where
thoughts are respected
for being different, not wrong
During breaks in between sessions,
we play the CoC guideline video
The CoC guideline video will be played
in between sessions this year as well
so please take a look at it
We are also promoting the CoC
on our official social media account
Also, by slightly applying
the Universal Design
we are preparing financial support
and a barrier-free location for the event
We still have a long way to go
but we are expanding one step at at time
Also, we educated our PyCon Korea
Organizing Team on disability awareness
We invited specialists and asked a lot
of questions during the session
to raise disability awareness
We provide real-time captions
and subtitles for all videos
shown at PyCon Korea 2020
We aren't perfect
That's why we completely
revised the CoC in 2019
Before its revision, the entire PyCon Korea
Organizing Team held a human rights workshop
and to revise the CoC
we held a 2-day camp dedicated to discuss
the CoC and also held regular debates
It took about 4 months
Before distributing the revised CoC,
we received outside consultation
and even legal consultation before
adding it to our agreement
Also, in 2020, we revised the CoC so that
it can be applied to online environments
Every year, before the event
we hold an internal workshop to
refresh our knowledge on the CoC
Please give us suggestions
on how to improve the CoC
We want to build it together
If you run into a problem,
please report it to us
It will help us to make a safer environment
Did you know about this?
The PyCon Korea Organizing Team
members are also
ordinary participants as well as volunteers
Aven, when you found out that
the PyCon Korea Organizing Team
are volunteers who purchase tickets,
what did you think?
I thought it was interesting
When I first became a member
of the PyCon Korea Organizing Team
it felt like it was the host of the event
Usually, the host of the event
doesn't purchase separate tickets
But now, I know about 'Everybody Pays'
and that the PyCon Korea Organizing Team
are also ordinary participants
who are contributing in a different way
How about you?
As Aven said,
the PyCon Korea Organizing Team
are volunteers who are
contributing in a different way
just like how you haven't
merely purchased a ticket
but contributing to the community
just by participating in this event
Actually, the majority of
the PyCon Korea Organizing Team
consisted of people with jobs or students
So the members would get out
of work and work at night
and sometimes even until dawn,
during lunch hours, and on weekends
to prepare for this event
About fifteen people or so
gathered to plan this event
and we had to talk with so many people
that we were burned out
both physically and mentally
So when we communicated externally
we also sent out the message to
respect the PyCon Korea Organizing Team
since we are participants who
deserve to be respected as well
We are also putting in efforts to
respect each other among ourselves
When we run into a problem,
we don't focus on who's responsible for it
but instead on
how we'll solve the problem
We make decisions and
take responsibility together
The PyCon Korea CoC wasn't created
so that an individual or a minority
can give a good talk
We made it for us
Through PyCon Korea, we hope that
you support each other's experiences
and have a lot of conversations
while being respected
We hope that you grow
deeper, broader, and stronger
and spread a positive influence
to other places as well
We hope that through
this year's PyCon Korea
your world will become a step broader
Thank you
Wait!
Did you think this was the end?
We conducted a short interview on how
the PyCon Korea Organizing Team views the CoC
What is your take on the CoC?
Let's take a look!
My thoughts on the CoC?
At PyCon Korea, the Code of Conduct
is a very challenging subject
PyCon Korea hopes that
more people will use Python
in their daily lives and
at work in various ways
That's why we want to embrace
people from various fields
By participating in the process of creating
and revising the Code of Conduct
I've learned that there are diverse
people and lives in this world
and to embrace everyone, it requires
a lot of deep thinking and effort
Of course, my efforts as an individual
may be small and insignificant
and I am also probably violating the CoC
However, someone here is making an effort
and there are probably people
who know about that
That's why I, or we, hope that
we read the CoC and think about it
even more and take action
My thoughts on the CoC?
I think the CoC is a promise among
the participants to enjoy
a PyCon event that is safe and
where everyone is respected
When I first encountered the CoC,
I was surprised to see that this was dealt
at a developer conference
It's been about four years now,
and it feels strange without it
Outside of PyCon Korea, other developer
conferences are creating codes of conduct
which the participants observe
and the developer community is
becoming safer and more comfortable
PyCon Korea wasn't the first to do this
but I think it played a role in publicizing
the code of conduct in Korea
I hope there will be more events
in which anyone can easily participate
Thank you
Creating a CoC is a very
difficult task in itself
but I think it is a set of manners selected
from what's normative and ethical
that should be observed at the very least
Also, you could say that
the CoC is a measure
to allow contribution in creating a culture
where everyone is equal
If there wasn't such a measure,
I think it would have been very difficult
to create a culture that
accepts differences
Not just the participants
but those who are planning PyCon Korea
should all be respected
I believe the CoC is essential for that
I think I should also personally
make an effort to make that happen
but if we all observe the CoC and each
make an effort to be considerate of others
I think that will create a better
conference and a better society
Thank you
Yes, to me, CoC
is the reason I became interested
in diversity for the first time
So, to me, CoC is
like a friend who reminds me
about the importance of diversity
and helps me and everyone
to grow in our daily lives
Honestly, if I only thought about
my own experiences and opinions,
I would probably be stuck there
If diverse people gather,
diverse thoughts come together
and my own thoughts become
refined in that gathering
That would allow me to grow more
and make me become a better person
That's why I hope that with the CoC
we can all have a valuable
experience in which we can grow
To me, CoC is the very heart of
our slogan this year, 'We Are Pythonistas'
I encountered the CoC
for the first time at PyCon
When I saw the CoC being emphasized
in various locations of the event
I realized that it was an event that truly
embraces every person and every Pythonistas
It really hit home for me
As a participant and even as
a volunteer in the Organizing Team
I probably didn't observe the CoC perfectly
but by continuously checking on the CoC
I hope this will become an event that
embraces everyone as a Pythonista
To all of you who are watching right now,
thank you for joining us at the festival
We are Pythonistas